<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<subject>
<name>Bruno Siciliano</name>
<interview>
<interviewer>Where you grew up and went to school? </interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes. Okay, so should I start anytime?</interviewee>
<interviewer>Yes.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay, I was born in Naples, which is the third largest city in Italy, this was 50 and some years ago, October 27, of 1959. And I just recall a funny thing that the ICRA 2009, which is our flagship conference in-- took place in Kobe, it was-- we found out there is a group of us, who were born in 1959, so there's a number of roboticists who are, except me, known in the community just remember some names, Roland Siegwart from ETH Zurich, Peter Corke from Australia, is another '59er and Antonio Bicchi from University of Pisa is another one, and so Roland prepared some kind of nice piece to wear with the logo of the Robotic Society of IEEE and '59er, so this looked like a good year for robotics. And as a matter of fact, 1959 was also the year when the first industrial robot designed by George Devol, was made, was manufactured by Unimation, which is the company, one of the pioneer industrial robot manufacturers in US, so there must be some conjecture about-- around that year, that it was quite funny to discover years after. I did my studies here in Naples, I studied the so-called scientific high school at the Lyceum and then I enrolled into EE Electronic Engineering program here at the University of Naples, Federico Secondo where we are meeting, where I'm speaking this afternoon, and I did my-- at that time, our university system, we only had one degree, which was a five year degree, which is the equivalent to the Anglo-Saxon Masters. And I completed my studies actually in four and a half year, and then I was ready to-- just to leave and probably to move to northern Italy to work for one of the big companies like IBM, Italtel, all the companies in IT having a degree in electronic engineering. And then I had a sort of inspiration, because I got a proposal by a professor, a professor I graduated with, to start the PhD, which is called a Research Doctorate. A Dottorato Research in Italy. This was something new into the university system. Before 1982, we had no PhD, so the highest degree was a Master  and the interesting thing was, there was another professor in this department, was being my mentor to robotics, Professor Lorenzo Sciavicco. and at that time, he was just starting doing research in robotics. And myself, having been fascinated by a lot of teenager time readings on the books of Isaac Asimov, about you know, science fiction and robotics, I said robotics, to me, looked so diverse from the classical engineering, and I decided to join the program, because I was fascinated by the new field. At that time, Robotics was still in its infancy in terms of research. Robots were already popular in manufacturing plants, but it was a new field for research. And so I did, I started doing my studies in robotics. And my dream was also to go and do some studies and research in US. And at that meeting, which was the Romanci Conference, [ph?] which was a sort of mind storm in the history of robotics conferences worldwide, I had the opportunity to meet many distinguished scientists in our field, starting from Professor Bernard Roth, Bernie Roth at Stanford. And then I met also one of the most-- one of the brightest minds that we have in robotics worldwide, and I'm speaking about the coordinator of this project, Professor Oussama Khatib, Oussama, my-- probably, I think is my best friend, and since our first encounter, we became very, very close, very friends, very much friends to each other. And I had the opportunity then to go and spend one year at Georgia Tech in Atlanta, and I worked with Wayne Book, who was one of the distinguished scientists attending this meeting. And this really changed my life, because it opened up my mind, and I also, during the year there, I had the opportunity to travel in US, and visit other labs, and-- but more importantly, I started building my network of contacts, which has helped a lot, you know, during my professional growth. So I finished my PhD, and then it was time to make a decision. And I was very tempted to move to the US. I was offered a position as an assistant professor by Georgia Tech, and it was hard for me to say-- to drop this opportunity because, at that time, I was nothing here, because I had finished my PhD, my grant had finished, and that time, there were no post doc positions available into our university system, and I have to say that I was starving, and the only reason why I could stand it, because I was like a Mama boy, because I was living with my parents, and so I had no major expenses, so I could afford the luxury of doing research as a hobby, without money, without needing money. And so I waited. I was close to a position at Stanford, later in 1989, but there was-- time was right for a position here as an assistant professor in 1989, and I just ran for the position and I got it, and two years later, I became an associate professor, and eight years later I became full professor and after three years, I was hired at the University of Salerno as professor of automatic control, in 2003, I came back to my alma mater, to the University of Naples, Frederick II, Federico Secondo and here I am, and I direct the PRISMA Lab which is the lab doing work on robotics for industry and services, mechatronics and automation. In the meantime, I had cultivated all my international contacts, and I became quite actively involved into the Robotics Automation Society of IEEE. I've served the Society in many ways, I've been on the editorial board of Transactions, and ________ in 1991, and then I became a NATCO member, a member of the Admissory [ph?] Committee, in 1996, and in 1999, I was appointed to replace someone as Vice President for Publications. And then I was elected as Representative for Technical Activities and the apex, I think was in October 2005, when I was elected to President Elect of the Robot and Automation Society of IEEE, and this was almost like a dream come true, because I had just gone through all the steps of the society from a simple member to senior member, I had been elected to fellow, in 2000, and so this was like, kind of, I should say the culmination of my professional service to the society. And so I was President in 2008 and 2009, and I'm now, despite my, I assume, younger age, kind of retired, because I'm-- now my function is a Junior Past President so I continue to serve the Society with the nominations. At the next two years, I will become Senior Past President which means that I will be in charge of the awards, all the awards that our Society gives to-- to the excellence in our field, both in conferences and publications and of course in the professional achievements. So this is, in a few words, my story around robotics. And I'm just thinking about, I don't have the book with me today, in my office, but there was a quite interesting book that came out in Italian, I don't have a copy here in my office, because I just got it home last week. And this book is called  Literally it's like Galileo's nephews. It was written by a science journalist who is quite well known in Italy, and I was flattered to be invited as one of his, ideally, seven nephews of Galileo, and he chose me for engineering, so-- and there are famous scientists, Italian scientists, one of them for all these-- Giacomo Rizzolatti, who is a famous neuroscientist in University of Parma, and I was simply flattered that I was invited. And I was reading this book with my kids last weekend, because just I got it, and I was almost moving to tears because this journalist came to interview me and I told him about all my life and the result was a nice blend between my personal life, almost like kind of biography of the first 50 years of my life, and at the same time, you know, the 25 years of my professional growth merged with the growth of robotics in the field. So it was-- I like the result very much and I mean, it's a nice moment that I could share with my family. And of course I gave the copy to my mother, which, I mean, as you may mention, you know, she was kind of proud of her kids, you know. So this is in a few words, like, my growth as a professional, which I've only been-- I've really been fascinated by robotics. Robotics has been playing a big part in my life, and I think I'm lucky and privileged that-- for the fact that I have, besides a number of colleagues and professionals in this field, I mean, this community is like-- is a big family and with many of the distinguished scientists and colleagues, you know, there is a strong friendship which really gives that extra passion and devotion to this field, so it's--</interviewee>
<interviewer>So part of your PhD work, were you working at electrical engineering or mechanical engineering or were they sort of mixed together? </interviewer>
<interviewee>This was electronic. The PhD was tied to, I think electronic engineering like my masters, but clearly, working in the field like robotics, I discovered that my background was solid in terms of the mathematics and physics, which typically one studies in doubly, [ph?] but I was lacking in mechanical engineering and so I always liked to take challenges in my life, I like to just be on the edge, and when it was the time, when it was time to go to the US during my third year of my PhD, the challenge was to go to a mechanical engineering school, and I knew very little mechanics, because simply I had not taken enough courses in mechanics and so when I was working under direction of Wayne Book in the School of Mechanical Engineering at Georgia Tech, was also a growth for me, because I learned a lot about mechanics, and after all the years, I discovered that it was not even enough, because robotics was evolving in the meantime and I had to learn about sensor technology and recently I had to learn a lot about cognitive systems, and AI because robotics is becoming more and more a kind of complex and intelligence systems, and I think that nowadays, robotics has reached a level of maturity that the core methodologies and technologies are well developed. Now to further evolve, we need a lot of interaction with fields that until a few years ago, were probably considered to be really away, apart from robotics, but I think now, I mean, it's the time to reach those crossroads between robotics and all the other fields, and I think further progress will be by, I mean, our attitude should be one of openness and really enlarging our field of interest toward disciplines which, once were considered to be separated from robotics. So this sort of cross fertilization among different fields is happening, and I think robotics is playing a very active role into this process. </interviewee>
<interviewer>So the year you were at Georgia Tech, so what year was that, and what project did you work on? </interviewer>
<interviewee>I was actually granted by the-- at that time, they had a center which was called Center For Integrated Manufacturing Systems, CIMS, and the emphasis there was on automation, but my actual interest was to work on a new type of robotic system, of robotic manipulator that were becoming very popular. Those were flexible, flexible in the sense of distributed flexibility on the links. So compared to the classical rigid and bulky industrial type of robots, this was a sort of innovation, because flexible manipulators, Dr. Book had been working on flexible manipulators with NASA, with a project with a long boom, the long remote manipulator system used in the Space Shuttle Program, where the flexibility was induced by the length of the arms. Because this big arm, this big boom was supporting a platform where the astronaut would sit, but then flexibility was also used on purpose in the design to make lighter arms, and at that time, it was not clear at all, the enormous potential of this kind of design solution for the future application of robotics. At that time, flexibility was only meant to reduce the load of the structures, of the structure versus the payload, because typically a NASA robot can lift-- to lift a payload of ten kilos, must weigh 200 kilos. And the reason being that it must be accurate. So for precision, for accuracy, you need a very rigid and heavy structure. But thanks to the progress in the latest years on materials science and technology, we've been able to design lighter and lighter arms by using composite materials, carbon fibers and all the like. But recently these lightweight arms have become more and more challenging because the field has evolved and most of the research nowadays is on the so-called problem of human-robot interaction. So if you want a robot to share the space, the workspace with humans, you must go into safety, and safety doesn't come for free. If you have a heavy and bulky rigid arm, because a rigid arm can hit someone and can hurt and can even kill someone, so the trend into the field is to design so-called compliant arms, so arms that will be lighter in terms of the absolute weight, but also arms which, if accidentally in contact with a human, would cause less damage. And so nowadays, like, the mechanical designers are realizing light arms, there's one arm that was designed at the DLR, at the Institute of Robotics and Mechatronics, Professor Eutinger, [ph?] DLR, was a kind of revolutionary arm, because it only weighed 14 kilos to lift up a payload of 13 kilos. We've been using this arm into one of our UPM project. This was the France project where the issue, the attention was on the physical human-robot interaction, dependability and safety. But design is not enough. You also have-- you also have to rely on sensors and on intelligence, on control. So basically design lighter material are a sort of passive safety measure, but you also have-- you also need some active measure and you gain active safety by designing control algorithms [ph?] which are very fast, and in the case of an accidental contact with a human, are also able to retract the arm and not to cause any damage, any hurt into the human. So that the robots of the future will naturally be compliant both passively and actively, thanks to sensor and control and intelligence.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So what was the first robotics project you worked on, I assume before Georgia Tech.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Ah, this-- actually this was, during-- it was a project at Georgia Tech, because most of the research I had been doing during my first two years of my PhD, were like, I would say on basic robotics. Also with a background in control, I was working on robust inductive control but mostly at a theoretical and a simulation level, because at that time, I had no lab, I had no experimental setup, so I was working on a theory, so to speak, because, with a strong background in mathematics and control. So my first exposure to hardware, and I was very worried when I went to Georgia Tech, because I was not-- I've never been a good experimenter. As an engineer, I have-- when I started doing my studies in ________ engineering, I had no passion whatsoever for the hardware. I was more attracted by the scientific aspects behind electronic and the novelty of the field. So when I went to Georgia Tech, I had to get my hands on some experimental setup, and the first project was called RALF. RALF stood for Robotics Arm Large and Flexible. And this was a project being developed at Georgia Tech by Wayne Book, and I got to work in that project. And since then, I was involved into other projects in Italy. We worked also on some space robotics project, mainly with the European Space Agency and the Italian Space Agency, and this was a natural follow up because of my expertise on lightweight flexible arm, because flexible arms were being used to use the payload of the space missions. So-- and then I started working on-- or I think the first big project was, as I said, France, in which-- I mean the France is about physical and robot interaction. This was the first big funding that we got from the European Commission. And since then others have followed. I'm currently the coordinator of DEXMART, DEXMART is a large scale integrated project sponsored by the European Commission and it's about dual arm, dual hand, so these are called bimanual manipulation, so robots with two arms and two hands. And this project is about at the end. It will finish January of 2012, and so this is another project. And more recently, I've got interested into aerial robots, flying robots, and I currently have one project which is called iRobots, and there is another one starting in November which is a sort of innovation in the field because it will be multiple cooperating robots flying and manipulating some object and this is like a kind of innovation in the field, because flying robots have been used for several years, but only for patterning, for inspecting fields, coasts, you know, grounds unreachable areas, but the novelty of this project is that they will fly and manipulate, so it's combining the concept of robotic manipulation and take this into the air with a lot of easy problems-- difficult problems, I mean, easy to understand in terms of communication and ________ operation of these robots and also from a control viewpoint. I have a control background of controlling them and controlling the manipulation while they are flying. And this is posing a lot of challenging issues which-- this is attracting a lot of students, because it's kind of challenge. We have some flying robots in the lab, and the students, they have started to have some fun since a few months. And I think it's one field where we will see considerable progress, and also there is-- there are a number of applications where any robots might be advantageous compared to the classical ground mobile robots, because of the immediate accessibility of flying robot, but of course the regulation in the field are quite strict and severe. I was told by some Japanese colleagues that they were not allowed to operate flying robots in the Fukushima plant because of strict regulation barriers, and they were only able to operate some mobile robots to inspect the plant and to check the level of radioactivity after the disaster, the contamination. But there are a number of applications where I think air robots would play an important role.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So when you came back from Georgia Tech, to-- you came back to Naples, what year was that? </interviewer>
<interviewee>This was 1986, and for some bureaucratic reasons, I had to wait until '87 to defend my PhD thesis, because this was a new program, as I was saying earlier, into the university system, and so the graduation was delayed, you know, with no explanation, by a few months and then I was officially without a position-- I mean, nominally I was considered as a post doc. I remember one episode which is narrated into this book that I mentioned. This was very funny. One night I was working until late as usual, because I was not many of the time, and laptops, portable computers, I mean, laptops were not yet popular, so I was working on a desktop in my office and to work, I had to be in my office until after hours, and the security guard would come every night, past eight to close the building, and he would always find me working, and I, because with my white hair that I had since a young age, he would call me, Professor. I was nothing, because this was after my PhD, and I had no official position into this building, the building where we are talking this afternoon. This was a room opposite to the hallway from here. And that night there was a colleague, a real professor, working after hours, and the guard came to me and said, "Do you know this guy?" "Yes, of course, he's Professor DiMaria, [ph?] I know him, I know him well." And so he went to this guy and said, "I don't know you, but Professor Siciliano say that exception, you're allowed to stay because he knows you." He was furious, he went mad. I mean, he was yelling at the guard, it's like he is nothing, he has no right to be in this building, he is a clandestino, he's a clandestine. This was quite funny, well funny-- the day after I had a hard time with the department head, because I had to clarify, to clear up my permissions, because I had gained a permission because on my fame of working after hours with this security guard. But this was a time which wasn't easy, because I had refused offers to go to the US, and also I got an offer to go to Tohoku University in Sendai, which I refused. In a way, I have to say that I've always liked-- I like traveling a lot, and I have many colleagues and friends all over the world. And I love traveling and I love seeing them and I'm often on travel. But I feel attached to my roots, more than I thought initially when I wanted to leave the city and go to work for one of the companies in northern Italy. I think I am attached to my roots, to the city of Napoli, and also to my university. I feel this, and now at this stage I feel even stronger. So I-- when I had ________ it was good for me, it was important to have the opportunity to leave, because then you have a freedom of choice, and you know, when I was considering position in US universities, American universities, I was very tempted. But then I decided that I've had many, many friends and colleagues from my university time, who moved to the US, like brains who have emigrated, and they admitted they had made up a academic career, and you know, colleagues a professor at UCLA, at Berkeley and in other fields, but I decided that I wanted to do this in Naples, and I think it was kind of big bet and a big challenge and despite all the fickleties [ph?] of working in this city, which is not an easy place where to live, because of bureaucratic drawbacks into the Italian system, and also because of different concepts. In a way I'm considered like a kind of a visionary in the sense that I am a workaholic person and I work and I like to reach higher and higher standards, and sometimes people come to me, like, what for, you know, like, because the system is not really encouraging you, motivating you to do this, because professors in Italy are state employees so my salary is the same as the salary of any professor of my age and my seniority, so you know, I've done all this, if you wish, for the glory, for the beauty of doing research at-- I think at the worldwide level, and so this costs me something, but if I have to make a balance now, which is half of my life, I can say so. I'm happy that I stayed in Naples that all that I've reached, I have done with-- in my hometown. I think there's an added value to this, and this will be also a heritage, I think for my kids to attend this. And, I don't know, on one hand I wish that they would leave, or I'm trying to inject a sort of international attitude into their-- well they are still young, but on the other hand, I think it's good, you know, I-- they grew up here with all the good and bad, and the values that we have in our country and our society, and I think in our-- in my hometown, which is suffering from a lot of problem. Naples is often in media for problems with the garbage, with crime and that's the typical stereotype, but despite all this, I think it's-- I think it's a great place and also in terms of the-- I have to say the humanity of the people, is quite unique compared to many other places around the world. And I think the added value for me of having stayed here, and having achieved whatever I've done in my hometown with my alma mater, with my university, I'm kind of a little proud of this, and I think that in the end, it was difficult for me when I was younger, to resist the temptation of leaving, but at this point in my life, I'm happy that I stayed here.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So tell me a bit about how robotics has evolved in Naples. So you have one of, probably the first PhDs in ________ robotics. What were the first labs that opened, and what kind of machines did they have, and what did they--</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes. This-- the lab that I'm going to direct is called the PRISMA Lab. This, if I remember correctly, was started in, I think in 1992, 1993. At that time, we were lucky that we had big funding of-- in basic research from CNR. CNR is National Research Council and from 1990 to 1994, there was a huge project in Italy which was called  and thanks to this project, there was also a lot of funding on the labs, on the infrastructures. And we were lucky that thanks to the big funding from the CNR, we got the PRISMA Lab opened. At that time, and this was a time of making decisions, because my mentor to robotics, Professor Sciavicco, was the head of the group at that time. I was already an associate professor. I had big discussions, not really argument, discussions with him, what kind of lab should we start, because on one hand, I'd been fascinated by the advanced robotics lab that I'd seen around the world, where it would see no longer industrial robots, but prototypes, innovative robots, be them like advanced robot arms, mobile robots, a lot of work on sensors, and intelligence already, and to me, it was, whereas being a kind of a solid well rounded engineer himself, Professor Sciavicco, he wanted to follow a sort of bottom up approach, so he wanted to start on the safe side with industrial robots because he was convinced of the need of doing some research very close to the technology. And to do some research which could be transferred to the industry without going too far beyond. So there was a big discussion. In the end, he convinced me, because he was worried about starting something too futuristic. Having been no robotics, no lab in Naples before us. So and then we started with this sort of bottom up approach, and I'm happy to see now that I think this was a good choice, because I think it was the way to get-- to gain experience, and also to gain credibility with all the companies in Italy, starting from the big robot manufacturer which is Comau Company, you saw the Comal labs in the lab-- the Comau robots in the lab, and so-- and also it was very important to attract the students, because of course, you know, I always wish that in my class there is the future brightest mind researcher, but the other 24 students in my ideal class, they have to become professional, they have to becomes engineers, and they have to work for the companies. So to them, you must transfer something which is-- which they can spend in their working environments. So I think in a way, we continued our education program and we easily inserted robotics as a course and so we started the robotics course actually in 1990, the academic year in 1990-- yes, 1990, 1991, was the first course I gave in robotics, and we had lecture notes, and I remember the first year was really fascinating because this was a new course for us, and the four of us, my mentor myself, and the two younger guys who are now full professors at University of Casino, Professor Stefano Cabrini, and at University of Salerno, Professor Pasquale Chiacchio. At that time, I was an associate professor so they were assistant professors, and during the course, no matter who was giving the class, the four of us would attend all the classes with one goal, try to just improve the contents. And we were very, very critical towards one another, because every class we would-- after class we would revise the class contents, and I was changing the lecture notes, and then after two years, I had become-- I became an associate professor, so this became my course, and then I started working on the lecture notes that I wanted to turn into a textbook. And the funny story was that I was looking for a publisher, and we had these lecture notes in Italian, of course, but I've always thought big in my life. I like challenging, and also having made some experience also of TA in US, at Georgia Tech, I had become accustomed-- acquainted with the university system and then I said, I had the mission to write a textbook both in Italian and in English. So I contacted one publisher in Italy, which was McGraw Hill, which was a subsidiary of the McGraw Hill Companies in US, in New York, and I say, I want to write a textbook in Italian and English, and the editor was almost laughing at me, just, you know, you can't write a textbook in English, because first of all, English is not an easy language to write, and you're not-- it's not your mother tongue. I said, yeah, but my level of English is good enough and I know how to write good technical English, and also I know the courses, the robotics courses taught abroad. And then he was hesitating, I said, okay, let me speak with the editor, and he spoke with the editor of McGraw Hill at the Frankfurt Book Fair, nothing was happening and then I think I contacted people in the UK, and then I got fed of this wait, and then I say, you know what, I will send my proposal directly to McGraw Hill in New York. So the proposal was sent-- at that time, e-mails were not yet popular, so it was the-- sometimes some package, some envelope would come in the mail and you could recognize, this is coming from McGraw Hill, so one day I got an envelope from McGraw Hill Incorporated in New York, and this was the answer to my proposal and the answer was positive. So the proposal had been reviewed, and it was accepted. So they proposed me a contract, and so I signed a contract to write a textbook in English with McGraw Hill in New York. Then I went back to the guy in Milano at McGraw Hill Italia, and I say, I have a contract with your company. They want to translate the book into Italian. And I got the satisfaction of being paid for the translation from English into Italian of my textbook. But this was the kind of honorable [ph?] thing for me, because they had been kind of reluctant, so this was the story behind the textbook. And then throughout the year, the textbook evolved to the second edition, and then McGraw Hill decided to cut off all the advanced titles, because I think they were purchased by some other companies and so then I had to look for a new publisher. And so the second and the third edition of my textbook, which, by the way, is behind here, it came out two years ago with my mentor, Professor Sciavicco and also two of the young guys at the time, Luigi Milani, who was my first PhD student, he's now an associate professor in my group, and Giuseppe Oriolo who was an associate professor working with Professor De Luca at University of Roma La Sapienza and when I think about the time when I was considering taking jobs and university positions in US, then I think at the end of the day, I can say that it's nice that this came out, because this is also a textbook which is a reference textbook in many, in many universities in US. And I think, you know, it's nice that it's been authored by a young person at the time who was seeking for a position in US, but now at University of Naples. So I think it's a way that just the loop has been closed in terms of all the-- if I think about the lecture notes that evolved into this textbook and all the story behind, I can say it's-- I'm quite happy that, you know, this project evolved, and I'm really flattered by the fact that my colleagues in US and Asia adopt this as a textbook for their courses. </interviewee>
<interviewer>And prior to that, what were the other textbooks that were available in Italian in robotics?</interviewer>
<interviewee>In Italian, none. In Italian, none. There was only a translation. There was a very good book by Fu, Gonzalez and Lee. Lee is, George Lee is a professor at Purdue University, he's almost at the end of his career, he's almost retired, and well he's a dear friend, and this was the only textbook which was available in Italian as a translation, but I have to say that the translation was quite awkward, because apparently it's been translated-- it had been translated, I mean, the part on sensors, and, let's say, intelligence was fine, but the part on mechanics and control was less fine, because the terminology was a little bizarre, because apparently it had been translated by someone who was a professor in computer science and he was less familiar with all the technical terms and the lingo of mechanics and control and mechatronics. So this was-- and I just come to know last week, that this-- Springer signed a contract with a publishing company in China so this is going now to be translated in the Chinese language, and I think they have an initial agreement for 2,000 copies. I think it's by Quian [ph?] University Press, I can't remember the details, but this will be also in Chinese.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And prior to that, I know one of the big textbooks was Lou Paul-- </interviewer>
<interviewee>Lou Paul, Lou Paul is the bible. Actually, Lou Paul, I remember, when I started my PhD, I was studying on-- it's one of the books. It's up there, ________ the green one up there, behind the little robots. That's Lou Paul textbook, which was like the reference. This was a kind of precursor, because it came out in the early '80s, so when I started my PhD in '83, this was like-- this was the reference book and I remember the day in 1995, I was at a symposium in Herrsching, near Munich, and the symposium was being hosted by Garth Hertzinger, actually, DLR, this is the International Symposium of Robotics Research, which is like a top quality meeting. This is very, very-- and it was the first time I had been-- it is only by invitation and was the first time I was invited, and I remember the time in which I was at one of the sessions, and actually I was sitting next to Lou Paul. Lou Paul has not been attending robotic conference since the late '90s, but I had met him. Actually I had visited him once after my stay at Georgia Tech, which was all the network contacts, so I visit him at his ________ club at U Penn. and so I was meeting him again, and I was in a session, and a guy came with a little package from DHL and it was McGraw Hill, and they were delivering the first copy of-- I had goose bumps to remember this, episode, the first copy of the new textbook written by myself and Professor  Sciavicco. And I opened the package, and there couldn't be a better time to open this package, sitting next to Lou Paul. This was quite a coincidence and then I decided to give that copy to him, because I mean, there's no better person. And then he came back later with some comments and he liked-- of course, you know, the textbook had been much influenced by-- at that time, there were already other textbooks available, because this was actually almost 15 years later-- after his first textbook. There were good books by Mark Spong and Vidyasagar. Mark Spong was a professor at the University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign, is Dean now at the University of Texas in Dallas, Dean of Engineering, and the new book is also with Seth Hutchinson who is also very well known in the community, as the current Editor in Chief of the Transactions in Robotics and a dear friend of ours, with Alessandro and others. And there was also a book by Hassan and Zlotin from MIT, and there were quite-- there was also a book by ________ Hoshikawa from Kyoto University, a book from MIT Press. So of course my own textbook had been-- had benefited from all these other textbooks. I tried to give a sort of-- one thing, and of course there was the other, I forgot to mention, but I think it was the most widely adopted book, was John Craig, Stanford University. John Craig was a student of Bernie Roth at Stanford and his book was-- has always been one of the most widely adopted textbooks in the field. John is no longer in the research community. He's been working for-- adapting for SILMA which is a company in the Silicon Valley and I've seen him once in a while, you know, when he shows up to ISRR and all people come to IRIS because it's in San Francisco, so I mean, being a friend of Oussama, maybe I will see him again. So of course my own textbook had benefited from those textbooks in many ways. Of course, you know, being published later, it was also-- for instance, we had a toolbox, a MATLAB toolbox that came with the textbook. This was a nice addition for the fact that, you know, just MATLAB had become sort of the reference software in the field, and so I mean-- and so this was 1995, and now we are, like, 16 years later, and so this is the third edition of the textbook. And of course, in the meantime, those books, those successful books like Craig, and Spong, Vidyasagar and Hutchinson, are also in the third edition, and I think maybe these three books are-- have, like, the largest share of adoption worldwide, and I mean, I like the other two very much, because it's-- but it's-- robotics is not-- it's growing, but I mean, you don't write a textbook because you want to become rich, you want to write about, I don't know, internet or physics or basic subjects, but it's fun. I think the importance of a textbook in-- especially in the field is very important, and lucky enough in the community, we had this huge project, which is the Handbook of Robotics that I coordinated with Oussama Khatib, and that's more like for, I mean, just-- it's good for the people starting doing research, so it's more like-- </interviewee>
<interviewer>How did that project come together? </interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, the story was-- started in 2002. At that time, we had a good contact with Springer. At that time-- the whole story started in Europe, because in Europe we had a Network of Excellence, funded by the European Commission. This was called EURON. EURON stood for European Robotic Research Network, and one deliverable of that project was a new series of books in robotics. At that time, I established a contact with Springer, because my textbook had just been moved from McGraw Hill to Springer, so I had a good liaison, a good contact with Springer, and then, together with a colleague from the University of Amsterdam, we were invited by Springer in Heidelberg. We went there, and that time, there were some robotics books published by Springer, but they were scattered in different series, like lecture notes in control information sciences, lecture notes in computer science, but there was no dedicated series to robotics So we sat together and we agreed to launch a new series of robotics books. And this is-- these are the books that you see behind me, the red and blue books. The series is STAR Series, STAR stands for Springer Tracts in Advanced Robotics and so the STAR series started in between the end of-- I think it was the end of 2000, the beginning of 2001, but even though it was European project, I wanted-- I had the ambition to make it international. And then I invited Oussama Khatib, because we always wanted to do something together. Okay, let's do the editorship of the series. So the editors are Oussama Khatib, Franz Groen and myself. And so we launched the STAR series. And the STAR rapidly became as the best selling series at Springer, so there was a really sound start with really good volumes. And a year later I got an e-mail from Thomas Litzinger, who is the Engineering Editor with Springer, and they had just launched the new series of handbooks. And he said, are you interested in writing a handbook on robotics? And I said, oh, that's huge, a handbook is like an encyclopedia, that's-- no, that's-- and then I-- but I was kind of intrigued by the idea, it's like this will be like ________ reference in robotics. And then I just, let me think about, and then I decided, I'll call Oussama. So I called Oussama. I remember I was taking the original phone call, I was about to board a plane, as often, especially since the year 2000, and I call him from the airport, and I told him, should we do it? I just-- I wanted to talk to him before. I could have forwarded the e-mail, but I think it was something that I wanted to tell him in person. So I called him and I say, should we do it? And then our initial answer was positive, and we met in Washington, D.C. actually in Crystal City, because ICRA 2002 was there, so we met with Oussama and the Engineering Editor, so we went to lunch to a nice Italian restaurant, and this was the, you know, like the first stone of the handbook, and we decided to start working on this. And so, and these were six intensive years of work from 2002 to 2008. In my e-mail folder for the handbook, at the end of the project, I was counting something like, I think, 11, 12,000 e-mails stored, which, I mean the first three years was kind of slow, but I mean, I think this was an incredible load also of coordinating all the authors, but I think it was kind of recognition for the whole community, because I think altogether, we wrote a kind of milestone, and it's a kind of piece of 50 years of history of robotics and also our plan is to update the handbook and to work on the second edition to appear in 2013 with multimedia attachment. So the handbook was also, for me it was a way to-- it was an opportunity for a further growth, because there were some fields in which I was not so familiar and so the effort of coordinating all this group of editors and authors and also in terms of the international contacts, it was quite a challenge to get authors from different institutions, from different countries and often the case, from different schools of thought to work together, and because in many cases, it was the first time they were coauthoring something together, so it was a real challenge. And I think, in the-- and also there was a kind of peer review of all the chapters, and in the end, I think this was a nice service, that I think we provided to the scientific community, especially to those new to robotics, that they want to start in robotics. So even though, of course I attach it to my textbook and those research project, I think the handbook has been, and probably it will be, it will stay the biggest professional project I have-- I pursued in my career, I think. And it's nice that, you know, I had the privilege of sharing this with Oussama, because as I said, you know, we are colleagues, but also we are really, like brothers, close friends to each other, and I think there would be no better opportunity to do something together, other than then handbook. So I'm happy that this has happened in my life, because it is an enrichment in all possible ways, you know, professionally and humanly and in terms of the friendship and in terms of, yeah, the-- really the opportunity of seeing all this gathered into this thick volume, which is behind, it's lying on the table, it's like a very thick tool. And I think I'm kind of worried because, of course, a second edition will have some extension but I think we are already beyond the physical bound of having all this into one volume, so I don't know how it will work. But maybe, I don't know if we can go only electronically, because of course the way to go is like electronic publishing and in fact this has been-- I was getting the figures from the publisher last month, and apparently this has been the book with the largest number of downloads electronically from the Springer website, because the people find it useful to download one or more individual chapters, because they are written in a kind of self contained way, so like whoever's work is willing to start, I don't know, research in medical robotics, come here and the best chapter written by Russ Taylor at JHU Johns Hopkins University and Paolo Dario at the school of Sant'Anna, they are like two of the coauthors of this, so in a way, the authors were clearly selected, possibly ________ to the best people, and we were very surprised that everybody agreed with-- it's a lot of work, of course, but I think once we got a critical mass kernel of the top scientists, it was easy to recruit the others who were missing, because in a way, they felt they want to be part of the venture, and it's all in here, so it's good. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Great, great. Just to go back to the textbook a little bit, subsequent, have there been other Italian language textbooks, or is most of the robotics in Italy being taught in English, or Italian?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Right now, I'm teaching two courses. One is called Control of the Robot, Robot control, it's in Italian, and the other course is, it's titled, Advanced Robotics and since three years I've been teaching it in English. What happens is, so the first course is compulsory, for all the students, in automation engineering, the second course is elective, so only the students who are really willing to do a thesis in robotics, they choose advanced robotics. But what happens is that most students decide-- the book is available both in English and in Italian, but most students decide to buy the book in English because it's also a good opportunity for them to know the technical language in the field, because one way or the other, they're going to work by using English in their professional career. I have to say though, that Italian, like German and French and Spanish is a kind of major language, in the sense that most textbooks are either translated or available directly in the mother language, whereas in countries like The Netherlands, or Denmark or Sweden, it's often the case that even at the masters level, the books are all in English, and even the courses are taught in English. So I had-- having decided to write a textbook I couldn't refrain from writing also in Italian, but in my mind, I always wrote first with an English cut. You know, I had in mind to write a book for the international, and also for the-- if you wish for the Anglo-Saxon university system, because the Italian language is also different and it's much more flourished, and the sentences are longer and the style of writing is completely different, so even when I was-- I mean, the Italian version of the textbook is quite unique if you compare, even with the technical books in Italian, because it's intentionally crisp and short, with short sentences, because it was actually conceived as a translation from the English language, and I think the students, they like it this way, because Italian is a language-- I've always live into myself, also being a Neapolitan with a sort of open character and friendly and social, so I used to say, especially to my friends in Germany, that when I work, I'm very German, off work I'm very Neapolitan. So I'm living this kind of dichotomy into my soul, into my innest [ph?] brain and feelings, because I'm very German, very well organized when I work, but clearly, you know, just being born in this city, and having grown up in this city, living in this city, I very much have a kind of open spontaneous and haptic personality, so I live this kind of blend, which in a way could be reflected about the technicality of a language like English, which is almost like a computer language in many ways, and actually, I have to say, I have to confess, that for me, it's easier to give a talk in English than in Italian. I mean, just-- my colleagues, my friends have been telling me that when they come to a conference or a talk, or even the class, a lecture, it's easier for me to-- in English, because it's kind of technical language, whereas in Italian, I think I-- I think I'm consciously concerned about using the most beautiful Italian and the richest and the most flourished, because you can talk Italian at very-- at the different levels, and to talk in a kind of elegant and flourish and appealing Italian, it's not-- it's by no way easy. And so it's even more difficult for a technical field like robotics, so I'm teaching both in Italian and English, and I forgot to mention that we also have a masters here, starting this academic year, so the first ________ masters has taken place. It's actually, the word masters is different from master of science abroad, because a masters here, is a sort of a specializing one year course after the lauria, [ph?] which is equivalent of the master of science. So in order to access our masters, you must already have a master of science of the equivalent of a lauria, so this new master of-- this new masters in robotics intelligence systems, all the courses are in English, the courses, the labs and the seminars, because we also have students coming from abroad. So the whole program is in English, and all the interaction by e-mail with colleagues, and we have a scientific board, is in English, because you know, it's meant to be a sort of international masters for the foreign students, and we have a few foreign students that are studying and are doing this masters here in Naples. So at the end of the day, of course if I go to a-- sometimes I've given public talks to schools, because robotics is also important to take it to the schools and to the younger generations. Two years ago there was a huge science event here in Naples. This is an annual event which is called, Futuro Remoto, literally translating, Remote Future. So it's usually a way to approach people to science and future, and the 2009 edition was devoted to robotics, to robots. We had ASIMO, we had the show with the ASIMO humanoid robot and so Oussama came to Napoli for the grand opening, and we had the opening with a crowded hall of more than 3,000 people and a lot of kids from the schools, and we gave this talk. I talk in Italian and Oussama, of course, talk in English and I was translating for the audience. But other than literally translating, I was summarizing piece by piece what he was saying, otherwise it would become boring, you know, like the literal translation. Also because he had a lot of pictures and videos, so it didn't really need-- also because it was a kind of dissemination talk, not a technical talk by any way, and then I remember, of course, people knew that there would be the ASIMO show, but I was instructed by the ASIMO team during my talk to simulate I had-- I had cough. I just stopped talking, I had a dry throat, and I was coughing and then I was asking one of the girls, one of the hostesses, like, ________ to bring me a glass of water. And from the backstage, ASIMO came out and served me a glass of water. And even if I had tried this in the backstage, I was-- I got goose bumps, because with this kind of live 3,000 people and ASIMO was slowly walking to me, just bringing me a tray with a glass of water, and it was compliant enough, I pick up my glass of water, and I drank it, and I remember, like, it was my mother sitting on the front row, and she saw this robot and she told my kids, I think there is a child inside the suit, because ASIMO looks like an astronaut. I think this is not a machine, there is a child, there is a person, a human being inside the cover, because ASIMO is quite natural. But this is a sort of kind of mind storm, because in the manufacturing, and in fact, I think some of the-- yeah, some of the big-- the biggest European robot-- the biggest robot manufacturers worldwide, are from Europe and Japan. Surprisingly enough there is no big robot manufacturer in US, despite the fact that robots, as I was saying earlier, were introduced first in US. For some reason the industrial robotics industry was not nurtured in US, and it was soon the case that the attention was more toward, let's say, service robotics and not the traditional industrial applications. I mean, nowadays, I mean, like, two thirds of the world market is still in industrial robotics, although there are studies in the sector that foresee that in 20 years from now, two thirds of the market will be in service robotics. Service not only for advanced new industrial applications, other than the typical automotive, because most of the market is in the car industry, both for the assembly and for the motor parts, and more recently, for the automotive, all the intelligent system, like parking facility, you know, it's the concept of drive by wire, you know, smart cars and smart roads, autonomous vehicles or semi-autonomous vehicles, and things like this. So going back to Europe, we had this strong robotics and automation tradition. But in a way, I felt that in the late '80s and early '90s, we were a little, I think kind of lagging behind the most advanced research in US on field robots and studying around that time in Japan on service robots, because the Japanese started investing in the middle '90s in their humanoids project or approaches where they were developing biologically inspired robots, like, let's say, zoomorphic like the robot dog or the robot seal, Paro, because I think it's a kind of cultural, and also historical and even religious issue behind, because the Japanese have always been convinced that a machine, to be accepted by humans, must have the same shape and appearance of humans, so that's why they have insisted so much in developing a biologically inspired machines. When Sony made AIBO, the robot dog, available, they had orders on internet in Japan, and they sold 2,500 pieces in a few hours. It took six months in the rest of the world to sell the same number, the same amount of pieces. Because I don't think that, in the western culture, we are prepared to interact with a machine that has the appearance, that has the anthropomorphic or kind of zoomorphic appearance. I think our relationship with the machine is different and we like machine to be a machine and to be clearly distinguished from the humans. So this is one issue and I think Europe had not found yet its way toward advanced robotics. There were some applications of field and service robotics, but in a way they were not mature enough. Things started changing in the middle '90s, also, I have to say, thanks to the financial support of the European Community, because robotics became one of the topical areas for funding and we had the opportunity of carrying out research at the European level, and to cooperate with partners from other countries, because before, there had been some success stories, only on a local basis. For instance, there was a huge project being created after BLR, that took to the development of the lightweight arm that was manufactured by KUKA later, but this is a local success story between BLR and KUKA, which is kind of local reality, and so was the case for ADB in Sweden, with Lund University and also so was the case for us in Italy, working in consulting and working in close cooperation with Comau, we designed the complete control system for the third and fourth generation controllers for Comau and so there was kind of local realities. But I think we were lacking a kind of inter-- inter-lab cooperation, and this was possible, thanks to the support of the European Commission. At the same time, there were some scholars, some researchers who had gained PhD, mainly in American universities and they came back to Europe, and so there was a kind of, I think we were in need of a sort of generation turnover, change of generation, and those bright minds with PhDs in US universities, they came back and they started new labs around in Europe. </interviewee>
<interviewer>And who are some of those names that come to mind?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, there are-- well, there are several. As I mentioned earlier, one of the '59ers is Roland Ziggurat, with-- currently Vice President for Research and Technology at ETH in Zurich, is--  </interviewee>
</interview>
</subject>
