<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<subject>
<name>Daniela Rus</name>
<interview>
<interviewer>If we could start with having you tell us what your name is and where you were born and when.</interviewer>
<interviewee>My name is Daniela Rus.  I was born in Romania.  I spent the first part of my life in Romania, and my basic schooling education happened there.  I went to a special mathematics and physics school.  And eventually my parents immigrated from Romania via some stops in Europe to the U.S.  And as a teenager, we arrived in Iowa City, Iowa.  I had a big shock  about American life, which is not at all what I had imagined from TV shows like "Dallas," which were the only shows that were airing in Romania at the time.  I did my undergraduate degree at the University of Iowa.  I majored in computer science mathematics, and I had a minor in astronomy.  And then, I went to Cornell University to work on my PhD with John Hobcroft [ph?].  As a student at the University of Iowa, I met John and he was giving a talk on the grand applications of computer science.  And at the time, he was convinced that robotics was the main big application, that computer science had made a lot of progress on basic fronts like theory, programming languages, operating systems.  And it was really time to package it all together and put it in a grand application.  And robotics was an extremely important and seductive application, so I was completely seduced by John's talk.  And because as a kid, I grew up actually watching "Lost in Space," and the robot in "Lost in Space" was what I often dreamed about.  And so the opportunity of working on something related to these grand childhood dreams were just amazing.  And I had an opportunity to meet with John Hobcroft after his talk, and he convinced me to apply to Cornell and join him in his research group there.  So that is in a nutshell, the story of my education.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So when you were in Ohio, was there actually --</interviewer>
<interviewee>Iowa.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Iowa, I'm sorry.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Ohio .</interviewee>
<interviewer>I always get those confused.  </interviewer>
<interviewee>So maybe we can edit this part of the tape.</interviewee>
<interviewer>I will be edited out of the tape anyway.   But in Iowa, did you see robots?  Were there already robots there, were people working on things like that?</interviewer>
<interviewee>No, not at all.  In fact, Iowa was where my family settled, so the first years in the U.S., I was primarily focused on being coherent in English, so being able to express myself in English, making adjustments between my education in Romania and the expected education at the University of Iowa, because there were significant differences.  So my math education from high school was strong enough that I was able to walk straight into graduate level math classes.  But then, I had to take courses like rhetoric and history, and in particular, American History.  And you know how the undergraduates' curricula are constructed, so there was a gap.  And I really had to make a special effort on the language front.  Also, for cultural adjustments and just in general to get more integrated with the American ways.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And in Romania, how does one get into the special math and physics school?</interviewer>
<interviewee>So at the time, so this was communist Romania, the education was very different than what it is like today.  So there were admission exams, if you wanted to get into one of these intensive schools, and there was a hierarchy, so there were the best schools and the next best schools and so forth.  But you actually had to take two exams.  So there was one exam you took in the eighth grade, and that exam was based on math and reading-writing.  And then there was another exam in the 10th grade, and that exam filtered about half the people out, and allowed half the people to continue.  And that exam was mathematics and physics, at my school.  There were other schools.  So during communist Romania, the Romanian leadership wanted to make sure that there is a good workforce for the future.  And they wanted to start this education early on, so there were a lot of technical schools.  Very few people got to stick to the basic education tract, and most people went to the so-called industry schools, where they would take classes for a couple of weeks, and then go work in the factory for a couple of weeks.  And in fact, even at the best school in my town, which is this high school called "Nicolai Chesk [ph?] School" I attended, even there we actually had to get factory experience.  So every month, we would have three weeks in school and one week in the factory.  And my particular place of work was a factory that produced spare parts for trains.  And so I really didn't enjoy that part of my schooling at all.  And because you go in this big, noisy place, they are workers that really don't want to be bothered with you, who have things to do.  It's not intellectually that interesting, but you still have to spend a whole week doing something there.  And you have to repeat this experience, month after month after month.  And so, I found myself learning how to use a lathe and how to use a screw-making machine and how to mold things.  And I never thought I would use any of this stuff.  I always thought, "Oh, what a waste of my time.  Why can't I just sit and write a story or read a novel?"  But in fact, in robotics, in my current work, I find that all this experience of building things and of learning how to run these machines is actually extremely valuable.  So you just never know what comes across your path, and you just never know how what you learn today will help you or hinder you in the future.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Did having these kinds of experiences with actually hands-on things, was that also part of what interested you in robotics when you heard about the --</interviewer>
<interviewee>No.</interviewee>
<interviewer>No?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Not at all.  No, the hands-on stuff was, like I said, I was just not interested in that in the beginning.  Although, the more I learned about robotics, the more I realized that a robot is the combination of a brain and a body.  And in my robotics work, I have been very interested in thinking about how the brain and the body match together.  And my interests are often in examples of autonomy for machines, where the kind of algorithms and capabilities we would like to implement require certain types of mechanical capabilities.  And most of the times, you cannot buy machines that have those required mechanical capabilities.  And so, that was kind of the flow of events that had me in a spot where, all of a sudden, I was interested in designing machines and thinking about new types of robot bodies, new types of machines.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And so, to go back to when you started working on robotics with professor Hobcroft, when you got to Cornell, what was it like there?  What was the lab like, what kinds of things were they working on?</interviewer>
<interviewee>So John was a visionary, and he had a significant group of people.  And he had a big puma arm, so this was one of the few labs in the United States that actually had its own puma arm, this really big thing.  And he was very interested in the capabilities of this puma arm.  And I remember some people were working on tying knots with a robot, so rob manipulation, which is really remarkable to think that this was a problem that was being considered in the ‘80s because it's still a problem that we haven't solved.  We still don't have robots capable of doing flexible body manipulation.  John is also someone who has contributed fundamentally to computer science.  He is a very distinguished scientist, very visionary.  And in computer science, he is very known for his depth of thinking and for his theory work.  So to continue in that spirit, John was also developing or looking at the theory of robot algorithms.  And in fact, he has some of the fundamental results on the piano movers problem.  So he had people in his group who were interested in theoretical aspects of robotics.  When I arrived at Cornell, he was actually interested in what you could do if the robot was a little bit more flexible than the puma arm.  And Ken Salisbury was building a very cool multi-finger dexterous hand, the UMIT [ph?] hand was being developed at the same time.  And so, John gave me a challenge that translated into some theoretical questions about how could you use dexterous manipulation to achieve a more capable manipulation than what was possible with a puma arm that had a pinch gripper.  So in fact, I still remember how we were chatting in his office and he was drinking coffee.  And he was saying, "Well, I wonder if you could get a robot to do this?"  And he started turning the coffee cup in his hand and says, "Yeah, how would a robot do this kind of manipulation operation?"  So five years later, I actually had some sort of theorems and algorithms and simulations on solving this problem.  So I ended up working on multi-finger manipulation.  And for my thesis, I developed a planning and control algorithm that used the fingers of a dexterous robot hand to reorient an object by some desired amount.  So you give me an object, you give me some rotational motion you desire for that object, and I could tell you how to move the fingers, in what sequence and by how much, to guarantee the accomplishment of this reorientation.  So this field of robotics is called in-hand manipulation because it was about moving something while holding it, rather than the kind of pick and place operations that previous robots had been programmed to do.  So I learned a lot from John Hobcroft.  I also learned a lot from Bruce Donald.  So Bruce Donald was a young PhD from MIT.  He was one of the Damasos Anaparazo's [ph?] students, and he arrived at Cornell as a first day professor, just as I arrived as a graduate student.  And in fact, he taught the first robotics course that I took.  And he was very cool and very funny and very warm, and so all the students loved him.  He was also very tough and he really taught us how to set high standards in our research and our behavior.  And one of my fondest memories from those times was at the end of this robotics course with Bruce.  He taught us about compliant motion planning and position force control.  And we had the opportunity to do some experiments on this big puma arm.  And then, at the end of the course, we came to know that it was Bruce's birthday in a couple of days.  So we thought, "Hey, wouldn't it be great to get a cake for Bruce, and then have a party, and have the robot cut the cake?"  So a bunch of us got together and cooked up this story, and made a plan for how to do this.  And we organized this surprise party for Bruce.  And I remember, together with Denish Pie [ph?], we stayed up all night and we programmed this robot, essentially doing way point programming, how to cut round cake.  And so, the plan was that we would get a big round sponge cake.  We had a knife with a blade about this big, which we attached to the robot's arm using duct tape.  And the program went a little bit like this with the big knife attached to the arm.  But it was a fly by night operation, so we wrote the program, but we really didn't have much time to experiment with it.  Anyway, to make a long story short, the big moment of the surprise party comes, everybody turns up.  And then, the guy who is tasked to buy the cake shows up, and he turned up with a square ice cream cake.  So we look at this thing and we say, "Oh, no."  Our robot program was not that adaptive, but now everybody was there, so we had to go through with the motion, we had to do the dance.  So I said, "Well, let's try, let's see what happens."  So the robot went  because there was a such strong resistance from the ice cream cake.  So sure enough, after a few struggling motions, the robot hit the singularity point and started doing this with this big knife attached to it, and it's a big robot.  It was a very scary moment, but it was also a great teaching moment, because we really understood the importance of adaptation and the importance of doing reliable, provably correct algorithms, and not just little hacks.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And was that still the puma arm?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah, it was the puma, yeah, yeah, it was the only robot that we had at that time.  Later on, we got some mobile robots from a company called RWI.  So we got two robots called Tommy and Lily.  So going back to my thesis, I never had the opportunity to implement my thesis algorithms on a dexterous hand because we didn't have one.  And the only hands in existence were at government labs, and there was great contention for time on those devices.  But when we got these two mobile robots, Tommy and Lily, we thought that maybe an interesting experiment grounded in my thesis ideas was to work on distributive manipulation of large objects, where effectively the robots acted like the fingers in my algorithms.  But now, there was no palm.  The object was on the floor and the robots were executing the motions without maintaining a continuous grasp of the object.  In fact, the floor provided that grasp.  And this work culminated with some demonstrations of furniture movement, using these two robots.  And so, those are really great times.  That work was done in collaboration with Bruce Donald, and one of his graduate students, Jim Jennings.  And we had a lot of fun together.  And we were very excited because, at the time, mobile robots were just beginning to penetrate universities.  In fact, Rodney Brooks had built the first inexpensive and reliable mobile robots, and actually showed the world that it is possible to have these devices.  And these devices truly revolutionize the work on mobile navigation, because it's actually very important to have the physical prototype, the physical device to show that your theory means something.  Because otherwise, all you have is a bunch of theorems in a book, and how are you to know that the assumptions in the theorem are actually the right assumptions.  Even if you do it in simulation, you still can't know, so I think it is very important.  So when dealing with systems that interact with the physical world such as robots, it's very important to go from theory to maybe simulation, because simulation is an opportunity to take some of the software bugs out, then all the way to experiment on a hardware platform.  And the availability of these inexpensive robots made it possible for lots and lots of people to develop robot algorithms, and that caused a flurry of results in robotics, and really pushed the field of navigation forward.  But when these first robots became available, there wasn't really much in terms of software environment.  So there was a lot of very low level programming of robots, and that can be tedious. And you really have to be quite an expert at something else, other than robotics, to write good programs.  And at Cornell, Bruce actually invited Jonathan Reese [ph?], who was studying programming languages at MIT.  He did his PhD at MIT with Jerry Sussman [ph?].  And he was working on functional languages, like scheme [ph?].  In fact, he wrote some of the widely used scheme packages.  So we had Jonathon come to Cornell, and he wrote the first programming environment for robots in scheme.  And he and Bruce wrote a very nice paper that year, called "Program Mobile Robots in Scheme."  And that was exciting because it was really the first time when, in some sense, the system side of computer science merged with the hardware side.  Because as I said earlier, robotics is really such an important marriage between computation and the physical artifact, the body.  But in order to do computation, you need to have the right infrastructure.  And oftentimes as robotists, we find that we think that is plumbing and somebody else will do it.  But if we don't have a way to systematically move forward and integrate the two parts, we will not have good progress.  And since then, actually the world has made tremendous progress in this direction.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And at the time, was each lab developing their own environment, or was there some sharing of ?</interviewer>
<interviewee>No sharing.  So at the time, everyone was building their own robot.  They were building their own algorithms.  And many papers were of the sort, "I built this robot, I programmed it to do X, and here is how the robot works."  And then, there were other papers that said, "I built this other robot, and it is doing task Y and here is how it works."  So that is sort of how it started.  But then, very soon, we realized that there is a need for some common abstractions that would allow us to, at least from a scientific point of view, to compare each other's work.  So how do I know that your robot that does X and my robot that does X have the same level of ability, and how do I compare?  Why is my robot better than your robots?  So how do you think about comparing robot algorithms, and how do you establish benchmarks and so forth.  So it took a while for the community to figure out the answers to these very important questions.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And maybe you can tell us a little bit about how that happened, as we go through the story.  I don't know if you have a feeling for .</interviewer>
<interviewee>So how did that happen?  Well, I think that the community started organizing discussion panels at conferences.  And oftentimes, the theme of the discussion panel was what is missing, how do we move forward.  And then, people started voicing the importance of pushing on the computation side, on the abstraction side.  So there was one person and another person, and pretty soon, people internalized these challenges and started thinking about them, and started putting results out.  And so, I think it was not one person saying, "All right, robotics community, let's get together and let's start doing X."  So it wasn't like that, it was a grassroots effort.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And what were some of the first projects that actually brought this together?</interviewer>
<interviewee>So I worked with Bruce Donald, in fact, on an idea we called "Information Invariants for Robotics."  And the idea there was that, in order to do a robot task, you need resources.  And there is some minimum amount of information that you need, in order to carry out the task.  And the important question was, what is this information, and how does this information translate into different information sources for the robot?  So I will give you an example.  If you want to push an object on a straight line, if you know where the center of mass of that object is, in other words, if you have a good model for the object, you can apply a force directly through that center of mass and you will get the straight line motion.  But if the location of the center of mass is not known precisely or not known at all, are you doomed?  Well, no, you can achieve the same kind of behavior by maybe taking a two-fingered gripper and placing it towards the boundaries of the face.  And then, the center of mass is captured in between the two lines of pushing.  You can push forward and achieve the same results.  So what is the trade-off, a precise model versus two pushing forces.  And now, you can even consider removing the rigid link between the two force lines.  So you can imagine doing the same task with two autonomous robots, but now the robots have to coordinate.  And so, you have removed the rigid link, but you have introduced communication.  So the idea of information invariance was to aim to articulate what is the minimum information required for a robot task, and what are all the different ways of extracting that information from the environment.  And at the time, many of the robot algorithms were centralized, and assumed that the robot had access to everything.  And people were beginning to work on distributed algorithms, but the theory behind these distributed systems was not very present, because distributed systems are notoriously difficult to analyze, even if you take a distributive system that doesn't move or a distributive computing system.  Even in that case, the approving, the performance of such a system is challenging.  So now, you had the extra degrees of freedom you get from interaction with the physical world.  It's even more complex.  So another interesting aspect of this information invariant theory was a method of automatically transforming programs.  So you could start with a centralized program that had access to all information, and gradually replace the resources used by the program with something else.  And so, you got to a distributed system. So you could start with a centralized program that has a careful model and the map and the central controller.  You could replace the map with sensing, because now all of a sudden you don't need that prior information.  And then, you could replace the central controller by communication.  And so, if you did these transformations following a particular structure, then you would end up with a distributed system that inherits the properties of the centralized system.  So that was really cool because the reason it was easy, I mean, in some sense it is much easier to analyze a centralized system.  You have all the information there, you can reason about the system, but it's not that realistic.  But if you can start with a well-analyzed system and transform it in a way that inherits correctness properties along the way, you could end up with the kind of robot system you want, the system that does not rely on too much  information and a rigid coordination.  And you could still predict the behavior of that system.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And then, it would essentially be more flexibly  adaptive environment.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Exactly, exactly.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And was this work that you did with Bruce also while you were at Cornell, or was that later when you were in ?</interviewer>
<interviewee>So I worked on this after I finished my PhD thesis, and I stayed at Cornell and did a postdoc.  And I worked on my postdoc with John, as well as with Bruce.  And it was just a great time.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And when you were thinking about the fingers, were you thinking of them as a distributive system, or this notion of self-organization came up when you kind of translated that problem into the individual mobile robot?</interviewer>
<interviewee>So the multi-finger manipulation problem was centralized. I was not thinking about it as a distributive problem.  In fact, it's a very challenging problem.  I would say that it is still not a solved problem.  I was very proud of my algorithm because it had very nice theoretical guarantees.  But the fingers required a range of forces that was not necessarily compatible with what a physical device could assert.  So there were a lot of issues.  In fact, just writing that thesis and thinking about what it would take to do it for real on an actual robot was an extremely valuable learning experience for me.  And the distributed part came about in some sense because that was the platform we had available.  These two robots arrived and it was just one of these things where it seemed like an opportunity.  So we had these two robots, we had this algorithm.  Let's instantiate some version of this algorithm in a context that could be executed by these robots.  But now, all of a sudden, these robots are not a centralized system the way the arm was.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And then, in your later work, you continued to work on these self-organizing and mobile .</interviewer>
<interviewee>Robots?  Yeah, since my days at Cornell, I have been very interested in studying autonomous self-organization, and really thinking about what it means for a machine to exhibit self-organization, and what kind of algorithms and what kind of bodies are amenable to self-organization, and what kind of capabilities can you actually extract from these self-organizing systems.  And I actually have almost two branches of work, but I actually see that they are deeply related. So I began to look at systems where the act of self-organization was a physical mechanical process, and this is how the work on modular self-organizing robots started.  So you have robots, these robots are mechanically and physically connected.  And you would like for these robots to self-organize, to achieve the body that is necessary for the given task.  So in some sense, this work was really aimed at thinking about what happens if your robot does not have a fixed body, if the robot is not a fixed architecture machine.  Can we even imagine those types of scenarios.  And is it possible for the robot to figure out by itself what is the best shape that is most suitable for the manipulation navigation, or sensing needs of the task.  And what would it take for the robot to aggregate that shape.  And when the robot is done with that particular operation, and comes upon a different challenge, how can it reorganize its body to match the new challenge.  So that is one set of problems I have been very interested in.  But there is the equivalent of asking those same type of problems in the context of swarms, where the connection between the robots is not physical, but it is virtual via communication.  And in all this work, it is important to realize that it is powerful to have multiple robot units cooperating to do a certain task.  It is powerful because it provides parallelism, it gives the robot a wider scope of actions, of perception values.  And it also is much more full tolerant, so if one unit from your team fails, you are not done.  You can carry on, you can eject the bad unit from your system and carry on with your activities.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So after your postdoc, you went on to Dartmouth?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes.  My first faculty position was at Dartmouth.  And at Dartmouth, I had the opportunity to start my own robotics laboratory.  And the first thing I did was to buy a pair of mobile robots, I called them Bonnie and Clyde.  And the next thing I did was I hired Jonathon Reese to write my scheme programming interface for these robots, so I really tried to replicate the infrastructure I had at Cornell.  But then, I also felt like I had the opportunity to think about different things.  And that is when I started thinking about self-organizing machines, modular robots.  And it was a very interesting time because the whole idea that you might be able to build these robotic modules that could move about each other, changing shapes, seemed like such a wacky idea.  But I was living in the woods, nobody was really looking over my shoulder on a day-to-day basis.  I was carrying on with my work on mobile robots.  But then, I had carved some time to think about these other problems.  And it was a fun time for me, because as a kid, one of my favorite storybooks was about the Barbapapa family.  Do you know about this?  Maybe this is a European series.  The Barbapapas are a family of blobs.  And there is the father, the mother and all the kids.  And these blobs have the ability of changing shape, according to whatever the challenge from the environment is.  So for instance, on one occasion, this gigantic bean invades them, and all the kids turn into cutting devices, and they in parallel chop down the giant bean.  And then, they turn into containers to pick up all the seeds, so that there isn't another germination step.  And then, they turn into cooking utensils to turn the beans into soup and have a party.  So these were really cool ideas that spark the imagination of a child, so I loved those stories.  And interestingly enough, I have a young daughter who, at some point, had no idea what I did when I was not at home.  But one day, she said to me, "I just dream of this world where, when you put me to bed at night, I could just reach into the wall and I could pull out a toy or a cookie, or I could just get everything I want from this wall."  So in some sense, this was an expression of a desire to have some sort of a smart material that you could adjust to whatever your needs were.  So I was very excited, I didn't know how my daughter came up with this idea.  But I just thought, "Oh, maybe it's in the DNA or something."   </interviewee>
<interviewer>It's your Barbapapas going over to her.    They are kind of blue and pink?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah, so they look --</interviewee>
<interviewer>Big and fat, and they have little like -- </interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Okay.  I never read it, but I have seen them.  They sell them and stuff in Japan that has them on them.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah, if you go to YouTube, you can see some of the shows.  They are really cool.  I think kids love them. In fact, I have indoctrinated my kids with the Barbapapas, so that was exciting.  But there were lots of long hours of sitting in my office with my new students.  Keith Scotte [ph?] was one of my students, and Marty Vonar [ph?] was another one, and so three of us sat in my office and we tried to break this problem down into some abstractions and then abstraction I was interested in at the moment was, could you imagine a robot module as a tennis ball, and so could you imagine putting two tennis balls together and rolling them and having them roll about each other by themselves?  So we made a lot of experimental investments that didn't quite work out.  At some point I thought, well maybe if you take the ball and you coat it with magnetic patches that you could program to be on and off you could generate the necessary forces to do this lifting motion but it turns out you cannot for very good theoretical reasons.  Then we had the idea of trying to do that operation mechanically, and we built a couple of different types of robots that use mechanical operations essentially to roll about each other.  So the first robot we built we called it a molecule, it was two cubes that had a right angle joint between them and if you built a lattice of these cubes you could program- you had four rotational degrees of freedom in each module so if you built a lattice of such modules you could actually figure out how to sequence individual actuations by individual modules to convert any shape into any other shape. And then we had another system we called The Crystal where the basic idea was a cube that could expand and contract by a factor of 2, and so doing scaling we were able to show that you could achieve shape change.  So those were the primary ideas that I developed with my students at Dartmouth. </interviewee>
<interviewer>And were you building all of them in house?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes, everything was built in house.  In fact, I was in a computer science department so my students were very good programmers but they were not really trained in machining.  And in fact, at this point, I realized that all of that high school experience in the factory was coming in handy but I bought a rapid prototyper so I bought  machine and I think I was one of the first labs in the world that used a position machine to make plastic robot parts and to in some sense simplify the act of machining a robot and reduce it to programming because our students were very good at writing CAD models, and was such a rapid prototyper you could do your CAD model, push a button and then the part came out a few hours later.  So now this kind of fabrication methodologies is considered a very current, very integral part of how robots are made, but at the time these machines were very expensive and not many labs were working with these tools.  It was also- that machine also allowed us to build beautiful and fun looking machines because the plastics were colorful so now all of the sudden our robots did not look grey, but they had these beautiful bright faces and that appealed to my artistic side.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Were the initial prototypes done in plastic too or did you have another set of things that you used to kind of think through earlier designs?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, we'd make paper devices or Lego so we'd try to prototype something in Lego but it was easy enough to print something that we did a lot of that.  And of course we went through a lot of design revisions.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And did you have funding for this, was this during your career award or prior? </interviewer>
<interviewee>So I had my career award on distributed manipulation and then Howard Morafef [ph?] was the Program Director in Robotics at the time and one time when I visited him I explained to him my ideas for how to build these self-configuring machines and he was very excited about the topic and so he helped me out by giving me a small grant and I forget what these grants were called, but they were essentially seedlings to explore an idea so was probably 50K, but it was really enough to cover some time for my students and to do so some original prototyping.  I also used my discretionary startup funds to help populate my labs, buy this rapid prototyper, to do things like this.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>Were there any other people at the time in Dartmouth who were interested in robotics?</interviewer>
<interviewee>No, I was the only one.  So Dartmouth was a very small department.  The Computer Science Department had split from mathematics maybe the year before I joined and we had a brand new building.  The facilities were very good but the department was very small and what was special about the department was that most of the faculty were essentially in my age group so there was a big explosion of hires and this was a really tough year to hire.  In fact, I couldn't get a job after I finished my PhD, there were no positions, but after the  then I had better luck, but it was still in some sense Windsor of our field in terms of hiring.  So there were some really great people in the department.  Everybody was ambitious, energetic.  We could be friends because we were at a very similar stage in life.  We were in a small department so we had to like each other and, in fact, this was a criterion for new hires and we worked together on a lot of other topics.  So my colleagues were not interested in robotics but I partnered with one of my assistant's colleagues to work on transportable agents.  So the idea behind transportable agents was building software that behaved like robots so a piece of software that could interrupt execution, move to a different place and start from where it left off, and these concepts, again, are taken for granted, but at the time they were new ideas and we were able to explore these ideas because we had the systems person and the robotics person who came together, wrote a grant, got some money and we were able to pull ideas from our respective disciplines to try to make this new thing.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And who was the person you were…</interviewer>
<interviewee>David Coats [ph?].  David Coats, and so while I was at Dartmouth my other most favorite collaborator, who became actually a collaborator a little bit later in my stay there, David and I started collaborating fairly soon after I joined, and I continued collaborating with Bruce Donald.  In fact, Bruce Donald ended up being hired at Dartmouth so that was a very, very special coupe for me because we had such a good relationship.  So what happened there was that Bruce got married and he had a  problem and at the time he was married he had the  problem.  Again there were no jobs but we were able to make offers to both he and his wife so it was just wonderful.  All of the sudden one of my favorite collaborators and my good friend was right there so that was very special.  So later on I was at the conference and I sat at some dinner next to Peter Cork [ph?].  Now Peter and I were working in areas that couldn't be more different.  So Peter had these big machines and was doing a lot of fielded operations.  I was doing a lot of theory and I was making little robot prototypes but I always admired Peter's work because it just seemed so real.  So Peter was really doing Robots real.  He was building these systems.  He was putting them in very realistic environments and he was getting them to work.  So I thought that was so meaningful and powerful and so we started working together and we sort of brainstormed problems and eventually we came up with two ideas that really combined his background with my background and one idea was related to sensor networks and so in that line of work we were really looking at how to take some of the algorithms my group was building and testing in the lab and put them in a realistic environment where we could use aerial robots to localize the nodes at the time the sensor networking was just starting so there were no results in the space and then we really built some of the most fundamental capabilities in sensor networks together.  And while we were working on sensor networks we came across one of my friends from Australia who Simon  who had been my student at Dartmouth that we somehow stayed friends and Simon was in Australia running the family cattle business and said to me, I really have this problem with fences because the farms in Australia are Gigantic and there is no way of knowing what is happening at one part of the farm or the other and I spend most of my manpower building fences and moreover I have to spend $500 an hour to hire a helicopter to move my cattle when I want to move them.  So I had been thinking about this ideal of virtual fencing and this is something you guys can do something about.  So the idea of virtual fencing was to do away with the hard fences and to replace them with electronic fences, a little bit like the dog wire but without the wire.  So with Peter we built the first virtual fence, which we regarded as a huge sensor network for cattle.  Then also with Peter we inspired by all his field work we actually took everything we developed together and put it in the field and I really learned a lot from him about how to make a robot system really work and how to do it for real, and how to put meaning into the lab results.  And it's actually very interesting because yesterday during out of our discussions at ISAR 2011 this came up as one of the most important challenges for the next round of robotics results.  How do you start from a theoretical result and push that theoretical result all the way into field and into real applications that somebody cares about and wants to implement.  And I think in some way the early work that Peter and I did together had some of that flavor.  So it was exciting to get validated in some sense.  So yeah, we built these virtual fences for cows and we demonstrated that we could put these cow collars and we could actually steer the cows.  We could stop them from crossing a line.  We could drive them in some direction of our choosing and that was also fun.  I still remember joking about how the cow was a very interesting robot because in terms of motion it's a non-holonomic system but it has volition so you don't have to worry about how to drive it but you have to worry about what it wants to do and then we were also kidding around about you don't really need a battery to keep it going.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>Just grass.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Just grass.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>Thinking about applications and having things go out in the world, does that later reflect on some of your other work like on the self-organizing systems were you thinking of applying them somewhere?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes, I remain primarily interested in developing robot systems that have enhanced autonomy and ultimately understanding autonomy in the context of self-organization.  But as a bonus I think it's also very important to see that somebody benefits from the results of this work and so in the most recent years I have looked towards environmental applications and talked to biologists about how our technology can be used to make a difference in their world and the first instance of such an activity was a whale tracking robot.  It took a few years to build this robot.  I started on this project because I was at the MacArthur Fellows Meeting and I came across Roger Payne [ph?] who is a very famous whale scientist and I believe he received his MacArthur Fellowship in one of the first rounds.  So he was one of the first batches of MacArthur Fellows and so I gave my talk about robots and he gave his talk about whales and I think we both fell in love with each other's work and then Roger started telling me about his passion for whales and all the challenges of doing whale studies, and in particular about 40 years ago he established a lab in Argentina and this lab is on the coast of Argentina at a spot that is extremely important for the migration of the Southern Right Whale.  Between August and October Southern Right Whales go there, hang out for three months at a time and that's where they have their babies and that's where they mate and they swim in 5 meters of water, 5 meters from the shore.  So they're really there, you can really see them, and about 40 years ago Roger started a census studies on whales but the way he does the census study is he sits on a cliff with a pair of binoculars and he looks at who goes by and he checks and in fact all the Southern White Whales have numbers or at least the ones that he sees.  The individuals are distinguishable by the callosities on their heads.  So it's actually very interesting to see who is around and nobody actually knows how long they live.  This is the first instance where somebody's tried to answer this question, but how laborious is that?  Occasionally they pay military planes to do fly bys and take pictures but the planes are quite high up and they cannot get very good resolution in their images and when they send helicopters they're so noisy that they just drive the animals away.  So we took one of our flying robots and we showed that, in fact, with this flying robot, which is very quiet as compared to a real helicopter, you can get maybe 10 meters above the whale, maybe the helicopter makes the sound of a mosquito so it's like a big mosquito buzz, but the helicopter can actually take a really good look at the whales, take unprecedented imagery and footage of whale behavior.  So we did this experiment with Roger two years ago in 2009 and this also provided another opportunity for Peter and I to collaborate because we need help with his vision expertise in parsing these images so that we can get the robots to follow the whales and some of those results are just coming out.  And in another work we were looking at underwater robotics, cooperation underwater.  That's where it started because my students were getting really tired of designing modular robots where they actually had to worry about how much weight each motor could lift and at some point one of my students said, can't we do it in water, because then we don't have to worry about weights.  This was after I moved to MIT and we started building these modular robots in water and then we connected to some labs that had access to water and one thing led to another, at some point we were doing some water studies and realized that people primarily used sonar when they make water maps, yet there's so much information encoded in the color that you see underwater.  If you look at the ship hull you can really see a lot of detail in the different colors.  If you look at the coral reef you can see a lot of detail about the eco system in color, yet it was not possible to take an image because if you take a picture in water and you're more than a half a mater away from your subject, that picture is going to come out blue and green and you cannot distinguish anything if everything is blue and green, you can't really see the shapes, everything is just amalgam, and with my students  we started thinking about color accurate imaging in water and how might we be able to provide that.  So we designed a device that enabled us to capture color accurate pictures that did not require post processing so you didn't have to mess with the image.  The image was taken to reflect the accurate color, and essentially the idea behind that work was to apply the inverse of the absorption that the water had on the light- let me start all over because I'm just rambling here.  So the idea behind doing color accurate imaging is to recognize that color is absorbed by water and it's absorbed in non-uniform ways.  So red is absorbed faster than orange and yellow and so forth, but the absorption  are known.  So if you know the distance to the object you're trying to image you can compute how much light of each color was absorbed between the camera, the subject and back to the camera.  So now if you have that information you can design an illumination device where you can control the amount of light of each color, and so you could effectively use this illumination device to apply the inverse of the water absorption phenomenon.  So we built this device and we took it to the field and it was a big success.  Most of the people that came across this device saw a use for it immediately.  So it's interesting some of these results happened by serendipity, and I think a lot about our field is by serendipity.  You know we each have our aspirations, dreams, research agenda, problems we would like to solve, but it's not so nice to be an island worried about your serums and robots and mathematics.  So when we come together and we exchange ideas with people a lot of interesting knew potentials, new ideas, new suggestions come up, and to me this is a very important part of my work in the field.  I have been in the field for more years than I care to count at the moment, and I have developed some very nice collaborations and interactions with my colleagues.  I look forward to seeing them when we have meetings, we always have interesting discussions and I always feel sort of richer.  I feel I have more ideas and I feel better off after interacting and you can see how in these two cases, in the case of the whale work that would not have happened without my coming across Roger Payne and it was a lot of fun to do that project, and still is, and the underwater imaging work was also enabled ultimately it boils down to my students refusing to build robots for the ground, so they wanted to do it in water, and the line of scientific meandering is actually very interesting, you just don't know what you're going to discover.  The virtual fencing work it wouldn't have been done without Peter, without Simon.  So I think that we focus a lot on the results and the science and that is very, very important but there is also a human aspect of our interaction and that is equally important.  And it drives the ideas and it drives the field.</interviewee>
<interviewer>The robot valet.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes, oh you watched that?</interviewee>
<interviewer>Oh yeah, I thought that was really beautiful I loved that.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Thank you.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And so how did that interaction or collaboration come up?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well it's all so serendipity.  It's amazing.  So I have a colleague at MIT with whom I always enjoy talking.  He's actually , this is Silvio Micali, and Silvio is very gregarious and very positive and I always so enjoy running ideas by him.  So when we meet at faculty lunch, he says, hey, Daniela, how is it going?  What are you thinking about?   I tell him something and then he gives me feedback.  He tells me what he thinks and so he's also so taken to bringing all his visitors and friends to see my lab because we have a lot of toys and one of his friends is the executive manager of Pilobolus and so the two of them were talking about, wouldn't it be great to have machines and humans in a show and then Silvio said, well why don't you visit Daniela and these guys dropped me a note and said, could we meet you?  And I happen to be a huge fan of Pilobolus, and I happened to be a huge fan of Pilobolus and Pilobolus started at Dartmouth, I've watched them many times, so there's lots of connections to Pilobolus.  So agree to meet with them.  They came to my office and they were just wonderful.  They were really warm and they were very- they were just incredible people.  We had a meeting of the minds despite the fact that they were coming from art and I was coming from science, and at the end of the meeting we actually started brainstorming what kind of possibilities might be for putting a robot in a human show, and here again the field challenge, right.  If you do an experiment in the lab and something goes wrong, well okay, you've had the problem.  But if you're on stage and the people watching a robot failure is a complete disaster so we really had to consider seriously all possible failures for our system so it was a fun project, but it also taught us something about our robots and about our algorithms and they way we use them and the way we make them  tolerant and so after that first visit in April I suggested- so I looked at my robots.  We have a lot of weird small robots, these self-organizing robots.  They wouldn't really look good on stage and then we have some ground robots and those robots again are a little bit boring.  I couldn't really imagine what to do with them because if the robot doesn't have a human-like body, if it's just like a garbage can it's really not so interesting to look at.  We have the underwater robots, which again you cannot put on stage.  But then I thought the aerial robots could be good but then how do you make the aerial robots visible in the darkness of a theater and then I thought, well if we cover them with lights, and if we could program the pattern of lights to convey emotion and to convey action as part of the story then maybe we can do something.  And I think they were a little bit surprised by that.  Their first reaction was, oh we don't really want to have a Christmas tree on stage, but then they came around and they really grew to like the idea.  Enough that they actually decided to put in the effort to do the piece.  And the piece came about very fast so they came back, the entire creative team of Pilobolus came to my team for three days, and I still remember, it was Halloween weekend last year, and we booked a conference room and we started developing the piece.  So Itimar [ph?] this is the man who made the first connection- we were all talking and then at some point Itimar remembered the poem The Serpent by D.H. Lawrence and pulled it up and read it and it was very interesting, it's an extremely interesting and powerful poem.  It describes the emotions of a man who comes across a serpent at a watering hole and who struggles with, should I kill it, should I not?  So what is my relationship with this foreign beast, and what do I think about myself as I respond to the beast.  And I think that actually set the tone for how we could think about the piece.  Then we came up with this idea, we wanted to have some sort of a triangle and we came up with this rough story of the girl or the boy in the woods looking for berries.  She comes across this strange creature just like in the poem, and there is some fear but then also attraction.  They get to know each other but then this is a baby robot so the mother robot does not like the fact that the baby robot is keeping company with these alien creatures and chases the human away, makes the baby obedient, but the baby really likes the human, and after the mother disappears the baby goes looking for the human but it's a little bit too reckless and hurts itself, and then when the mother sees that and needs the help of the human to revive the robot, they all become a happy group and we have technology and people together, sharing and living peacefully, and at the end of the piece, it was very important to me that the end of the piece was happy.  So at the end of the piece the human decides to take a trip to the robot's world.  So that was roughly the story and then from the story we have to actually choreograph it and the act of choreographing was interesting because we came up with- or at least the dancers came up with a weird list of abstractions so there were some behaviors that we're either robot behaviors or human behaviors, and I forget what they were but they would not be the kind of abstractions you'd come up with as an engineer, and so during the choreographing the dancers were picking the various abstractions and they'd say, couldn't you do X, and then X meant something for the robots and it also meant something for the human.  So the piece came together that weekend and then they came back in December.  We had another one or two days of rehearsals and then we did three Boston shows, and the audience was 3,000 people both times, I mean three times, all times.  And then we paused and we came back together this summer and we did a couple shows in North Carolina and about 12 shows in New York at the Joyce Theater.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>And how much of your team needs to go to help with the robots?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Two students have been deeply engaged in this and they basically became part of the Pilobolus family and they had a really fantastic experience.  But I view this also as a very important outreach activity because I think these robots did more for robotics than what we can do by going to visit this classroom or that classroom.  Giving an inspiring show where all the kids in the audience get excited and then get inspired and they want to know more, I think is really fantastic visibility for the field and it's a great way to attract the younger generation to the field.  During the New York shows the students were there with the robots so during the intermission they took the robots and they showed them how they work and they answered questions and that was a very valuable piece of their experience.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>And kind of a different way of portraying it  where it's more of a competition.  Those robots seem very lifelike in a sense, very different from a lot of robots that I think people would come across even in educational contests.  So if we can just go back.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Sorry.</interviewee>
<interviewer>No, no, this is great, but just in terms of keeping time and I know people get tired after awhile.  </interviewer>
<interviewee>I don't know what we're doing and I don't know what you have on your list.  Please feel free to stop me if I tell too many stories or I ramble.</interviewee>
<interviewer>No, the stories are beautiful.  Actually the stories are great, the stories are exactly the kind of thing that we're looking for, but I was curious, so you told us a little bit about the kind of things you were doing in Dartmouth and some of the people you worked with, and then we jumped over to some of the work you've done more recently.  Well one thing I'm curious about, in the beginning when you were doing the  amazing robots, were there other people who were interested in that kind of modular robotic?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes, so there were not many people, just a class of people around the world so Mark Kim [ph?] was interested in this field at Park.  Greg Terikchin [ph?] was interested in this area and he was at John's Hopkins.  Toshio Fukuda [ph?] and- can we stop for a moment?  What is his name?  I am just blanking on this guy's name.  Did you stop it?</interviewee>
<interviewee>Because he's very important but it's- how embarrassing.  I should know his name.</interviewee>
<interviewer>We can Google it if you want.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>You want me to Google it?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah, I have my computer.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>-- include the other people--</interviewer>
<interviewee>Who the other people were?</interviewee>
<interviewer>Um-hum.</interviewer>
<interviewee>The other people in the field were Greg Chirikjian, Mark Yim, Satoshi Murata, Wei-Min Shen.  And actually the field grew since those early days.  Many new people came to the field.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Um-hum.  And how have the questions that you've been dealing with also developed through the years in terms of these self-organizing and modular robots or other types of robots that you've been working with?</interviewer>
<interviewee>In modular robots, a very big challenge was to design the robot body.  And each robot architecture then had certain actuation constraints that translated into planning algorithms for doing shape formation.  And the first flurry of activity was really centered on essentially figuring out how to build a novel body and how to actually do the planning and these two questions were done in parallel.  But then as a science I think it's important to move away from architecture specific algorithmic approaches, so I became interested in more generic approaches for generating motion plans for these systems that enable instantiations to different types of architecture.  So the first body of work was inventing new robot bodies and planners that go with their capabilities.  And then when a sufficient number of systems were developed by my group and by other groups around the world, I actually became interested in asking broader questions about self-organization and abstractions that are required by self-organization.  And we developed an approach, a more generic approach, to controlling these systems, that could essentially become ___________ down to each type of architecture.  And after we learned a little bit about the field in this way, we started asking more practical questions about "How do you actually build systems that are robust and have some sort of believable behavior?" because there's one thing to say, "Well, we're going to have thousands of robots working together and making, growing, a third hand or a second head or an alligator," and it's another thing to actually build it.  Then when you have platforms that have 10, 20, even 100 modules you don't really get the resolution and the types of objects that we dream about getting.  You don't quite get the Barbapapa family.  So miniaturization became very important.  But also robustness on the experimental side and we learned early on that making and breaking connections was a very difficult operation in these systems and they all operated by making and breaking connections.  And I imagine doing that in parallel, because if you have a system consisting of a thousand modules and you have to wait for each module to do its thing before you can move another module, the time complexity is crazy.  So you cannot have sequential algorithms.  You really have to focus on parallelism.  So you have parallelism, you have a lot of making and breaking of connections.  It's a big challenge.  So how do you then solve these problems?  In the recent past, we have looked at two ways of addressing these challenge.  In the first one, we wanted to do away with the making and breaking of connections that is necessary to make an object.  And we call that-- so we tried to come up with a process analogous to sculpting.  So we said in terms of actively making and breaking connections, why don't we start with a block of electronic sculpting material?  And why don't we figure out how to peel the extra modules off this block so that the shape reveals itself much like the David revealed itself out of marble to become Angelo?  And we started work on a system called Mica [ph?] and that system evolved into a system that uses a smaller unit module that we now call Smart Pebbles.  Our unit modules are one centimeter cubes.  Eventually we would like to go to Smart Sand.  But figuring out how to package communication, computation, sensing and actuation remains the challenge here.  So when we built the Mica system, we had modules about this big.  They were about four centimeter cubes.  And they were essentially computers that had switchable magnets.  So you could program the connections on or off.  And we also had a communication system implemented through an IR mechanism.  And we had distributed planning algorithms that enabled the modules to talk effectively and figure out who is in the final shape, who's not in the final shape, and then all the modules not in the final shape could reprogram their connections by switching their magnets and they could just peel off.  They could just drop from the block.  So the biggest component in that system was the motor that rotated the magnets.  And so we were able to go from the four centimeter module down to one centimeter module by building something we call an electro permanent magnet.  It's about one gram and can be used to do program connections but also to transmit communication between the units and to transmit power.  So all of a sudden we no longer needed the space for batteries and the space for these complicated motors.  And so now we have these really cool pebble-size pieces, but ultimately the challenge is to go to sand scale grains.  And to build enough computation infrastructure that can actually run the algorithms.  What we're finding is that even though the smart pebbles have small computers inside, those computers do not have enough space and they're not fast enough to run the entire gamut of algorithms we have developed for this area of modular robots we call shape formation by sculpting.  So that's one direction.  The other direction is to do away with making and breaking connections altogether and replace them with a different action.  And here we are trying to make Smart Paper.  So this is paper that has embedded computation, communication, actuation and sensing.  And we are trying to get this paper to achieve the shape you desire by a process analogous to origami.  And we call this self-folding sheets and we have some successful experiments and some successes with designing this new type of body and developing algorithms that generate the planners that tell the system how to bend each edge in order to achieve the desired shape.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Um-hum.  And all of this is at ?</interviewer>
<interviewee>So this is actually quite recent work.  Maybe the pebbles and the smart sheets have been done at MIT over the past maybe two, three years.  I have collaborated on the self-folding sheets with Rob Wood who is at Harvard.  He gave a wonderful talk on insects and flight yesterday, if you caught him.  He's a young guy with tremendous creativity and potential.  And Erik Demaine is one of my colleagues at CSAIL and Erik has collaborated with us on the theory side on the origami planners.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And when you moved from Dartmouth to MIT, how did that move happen?</interviewer>
<interviewee>I moved to MIT because MIT recruited me.  And, in fact, when I was looking for jobs the year I went to Dartmouth my dream job was MIT.  And I interviewed at MIT and my interview was a disaster.  I didn't get the job.  I was really crushed.  And so it was very interesting that a few years later MIT, my colleagues at MIT, invited me to give a talk and then we started discussing a potential move there and after some discussions I decided to go.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Um-hum.  And being, since the CS department there is also connected with electrical engineering in CS, does this kind of make it easier to do some of this work since you're--</interviewer>
<interviewee>There's a lot of expertise at MIT and the students are trained in EE or CS and in fact, MIT encourages very interdisciplinary research.  So at MIT we have a matrix organization.  And we have our education activities that happen in departments and then we have our research activities that happen in interdisciplinary labs.  So the laboratory I'm in, the computer science and artificial intelligence laboratory, has faculty from many different departments and I also, I'm also able to supervise students from many different departments.  So my group at the moment is actually quite mixed.  I have students from computer science, I have students from double E, I have students from mechanical engineering, I have students from AeroAstro.  And we somehow find a way of bringing all of our skills together and the students help each other.  Naturally, if they have a strong background in one area they would be weaker in another area, but the students have built a culture where they help each other and they learn from each other.  So ultimately I think we are better off in this way.  And robotics really needs this, because robotics is really at the confluence of computer science, electrical engineering and mechanical engineering.  And these are the skills we want to see in all of our students.  However, if you look at how we train students at the undergraduate level, we do not train them simultaneously in all these disciplines.  But MIT is structured in such a way that it enables students to be multi-disciplinary.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Does CSAIL and the media lab, do you work with people at the media lab at all or are they ?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Two separated labs and I personally have not had any substantive interactions with the media lab but there are other colleagues in my department who have.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Um-hum.  Because both of those do a lot of work in robotics, perhaps with slightly different--</interviewer>
<interviewee>Different goals.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Goals, yes.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah.  Cynthia Braezeal is wonderful to talk to if you're looking for another name.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Yeah, yeah.  She's on the list.</interviewer>
<interviewee>She's on the list.  Great.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Could you tell us a little about who has funded your work through the years and if there are any other project or any other collaborators that you want to mention?</interviewer>
<interviewee>In my work on distributed networked robotics that's in my aspirations to develop the network science of distributed systems, I have done a lot of collaboration with Vijay Kumar.  We've had a very long history of working together and collaborating together and it's been really wonderful, I think.  Many results happened because of this collaboration and they would not have happened had we not interacted closely.  We have, Vijay and I, have several jointly funded projects and this has also allowed our students to get to know each other, to do lab rotations, to rotate as post-docs from one lab to another, so we really have a very substantive interaction.  The other person I worked with closely in mobile robot systems is Guarav Sukhatme from USC.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Just funding.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, funding.  So yeah.  Funding is always a toughie because there isn't ever enough money.  But my own funding comes from the NSF.  I've had funding from DARPA, I've had funding from ONR, AFOSR, the Army Research Labs, and I have a significant project at the moment with Boeing on manufacturing.  This project is actually pushing a collaboration with Howie Choset at Carnegie Mellon and Henrik Christensen at Georgia Tech.  And recently I started working on a very cool project funded by the Singapore government on providing mobility-on-demand systems using small robots.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Hmm.  And how do you make these connections?  You mentioned making a lot of connections in a sense serendipitously at conferences or during lunch at the MacArthur Fellow and things like that.  What are some of the other places where you would make these kinds of connections?</interviewer>
<interviewee>The connections happen because you're interested in the same topic and we follow the research from other groups and we read each other's papers and so if there is a natural synergy between the paths we set out to follow, then we start a dialogue and if it makes sense, a collaboration comes out of that.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Um-hum.  And I think we can ask you the final question.  This is kind of a fun question.  It's meant to go to the educational part of the site, but it's basically if you're thinking of new people who are interested in the field, young scholars, students, what kind of advice would you give them about getting into robotics in the first place?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, I would tell them to follow their passion.  So to the young graduate students I would give them the same advice I was given by Rodney Brooks when I was a graduate student, which is to do different things, to have the courage to try new things.  So when I was a graduate student, Rod gave me a wonderful piece of advice.  He said, "Look at what the others are doing and just do the opposite."  So look at what assumptions people make and see what happens if you negate the assumptions.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Great.  Thank you.</interviewer>
</interview>
</subject>
