<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<subject>
<name>Fumio Harashima</name>
<interview>
<interviewer>So we're going to start with where you were born and when.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh yes, this is my life.  I was born in 1940.  This is a special year.  Do you know that?  It's Emperor's Year, 2600.    But this is a-- they plan-- government plan to start a war this year.    This part of Japan. This is my kindergarten. And so this is .  Then they decided to start the war.  This a very strong war [ph?],  Arizona,  Hiroshima, 1945, March 10, Tokyo.  Completely destroyed.  The end of the war.  At that time we-- right to left.  This not mine.  This not me.  Primary school, 1946, next year of the war.  This building survived the war.  Still other war started in the neighbor country, Korea, the war.  This is a city of __________.  Incredible war.  Only sixty years ago now, 1950, in summertime, at the time of . Dinner. My family is a big family, five children.  My father survived the war.  Very lucky.  And he's-- in the summers at dinnertime he told us, to the children, this year is just a _______ of a century, 20th century, and this he said these children will survive.  We arrive until the next century.  And he said Japanese people will  his age is guilty in the war for destroying the whole Japan and he expected in the next century-- that next century, this century-- that he expect  on science and technology.  And my father was a physicist-- very well known physicist.  And then this is not the reason why I went to science and technology.  This is a totally different reason.  And this is high school, private high school.  It is like Eton in England, something like that.  Very special education.  I did not like it.  No freedom.    And for six years, from middle school to high school, I was always reading books.  Another time we are very poor and we cannot-- we could not afford to purchase books, so I went to library most every day after school, .  And I wish to be a novelist, not science and technology, until the end of the high school.  And I suddenly change my mind because I found I was not talented in writing.  And in university I went to a science and technology.  And I chose electrical engineering because this-- I believe this is the most far from writing.    So I went to University of Tokyo classroom.  At that time we have us on black uniform.  I'm here.  I don't have a uniform.  And came out-- oh, this is the teacher of this class.  Forty people, forty student.  One month ago we got together.  Only one guy missing.  All other arrive.  They all over 70 years old.  Incredible.  So you understand how our life expectancy is long.  The teacher passed away.</interviewee>
<interviewer>How did they allow you to not have a uniform?</interviewer>
<interviewee>I don't know.  And they go to ________ different direction.  All of them are in science and technology.  Some of them are physics, chemistry or engineering, or mechanical, aeronautics or something like that.  And probably I think over 70 percent of my classmate become the top executive of the companies.  And the other, professors.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>The University of Tokyo was one of, or was the best school at the time, and still?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Right.  Right.  Another time .  Engineering student-- number one engineering student are very small at that time.  So this is around 1960, and there Japanese industry started growing very fast so they needed good people.  So most of them went up, very top of the companies.  And they supported this Japanese economic growth.</interviewee>
<interviewer>How did you see the change in the way they saw science and technology in Japan after the war?  So since you kind of-- you've experienced the whole-- from the '40s to now.</interviewer>
<interviewee>I think most Japanese people have this kind of feeling, and then very good people, good student, came to science and technology.  That's a major reason why Japanese science and technology grow so fast.  And until middle of 1980s, we had very bright student in science and technology.  But in the middle of 1980s, people felt they are rich enough.  So good student or not started going to other area.  Now I'm sure science and technology student also not good enough.  And in most of well developed countries in the world, the situation is almost the same.  Even the U.S. or U.K. or in France.  But the difference is, for example, the U.S. can get the bright young people from outside the country.  The same thing in U.K. or in France.  And Germany was in a similar situation like Japan that they cannot get good people from outside.  But after the 1990s, the Soviet Union collapsed, they get good people from Eastern Block.  Probably you know that very well.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>But in the beginning when you had democracy justice and science and technology, why was science and technology seen as being so important for development along with these kind of other humanistic goals?</interviewer>
<interviewee>I think that people believe the first step is to get rich, and after the society has matured they feel society's goal changed to, number one, health; number two, justice.  It's based on rich society.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>So just like your son and daughter, right?  Health and justice.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, that's right.  Exactly.  So my daughter is a medical doctor and son is a prosecutor.  Probably when they are small children, probably we talked such a thing at the dinner table or something like that.  But they remember that.  So this is a typical Japanese history of  60 years.  Okay, let's go.  Can you see?  This is 1960, just after I enter the university.  This is student power was very active.  And two issues.  One is renewal of military treaty between U.S. and Japan.  The number two issue is government proposed a military service role, duty role, and then we fight it against the government.  And the first one we lost, and we won then the second one.  So this military duty role was canceled.  That was very good.  But other result of this one, student power time we didn't study at all for two, three years.  University was always closed.  But still they study by themselves.  No lectures, no classroom there.  I myself was very much depressed mentally, and I gave up to take job in the industry.  So I went to graduate school at the time-- we were young, time.  Mentally I was miserable, very miserable.  And John Kennedy, the president in 1962 or-- I'm not sure-- but we felt that the world had changed.  Many thing happen.  Castro.  Cuba crisis.  Castro.  Gorbachev.  John Kennedy.  But John Kennedy started the Vietnam War.  We are so disappointed.  Most miserable war.  This we closely defend [ph?] so we know it very well.  The only thing on John Kennedy, only good thing is that he started a civil role.  And it's a big influence on my life.  This is-- probably you are here, Institute of Industrial Science University of Roppongi.  Yeah?  At the graduate level, I studied here, and we started on our space program.  And we moved to another place.  This campus was too old, this building too old, and we moved to a new campus which is several kilometers.  And at this time, this movement, I was director of the institute.  So this whole building was my design.    It's a rough design.  I'm not an architect, so this is a rough design.  I enjoyed it.  This is my research floor, 1965.  This is PhD.  Submechanism [ph?], it is a nonlinear control theory.  Another example of this theory, I started power electronics just after I got a PhD.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>Who did you work with for your PhD, your professor?</interviewer>
<interviewee>It's a funny story.  Just after-- next year I enter the graduate school, my professor had a disease on the lung and hospitalized for three years, four years.  So no supervisor.  I monitored his laboratory by myself.  Only 22 years old or something like that.</interviewee>
<interviewer>How did you become the manager of the laboratory rather than some older student or something?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Because a student did not do that, but I volunteer for funding of education, so.  Many things.  And then I think this-- I got a PhD here.  Electro-drive [ph?] motion control.  And this is starting of manipulator control, robotics.  I think-- do you know Hideki [ph?]?  Hideki came to my laboratory I think in this year and he started this project, the robot controller.  And then this is interaction, __________, interaction between human and robot through computer intelligence.  And this is a big project, national project.  I'm the leader and I formed some team, not till later on.  And also this is a second stage of this project.  Well funded.  Oh, 1974 I attended this Industry of training society [ph?] a major conference called ICON [ph?], and I was deeply impressed by this area, technical area.  At that time they covered motion control for electronics of computer control and factory automation.  And then I think I was only one Japanese.  At that time this is still-- at that time still it's U.S. domestic conference, not international conference.  It was domestic conference.  And then this is a picture of that time, in Philadelphia.    He was society president at that time.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Who are some of the other people?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Here's Troy Nagle [ph?].  He was ________ to be president around 1990, and he's also some-- I think my successor as society president.  And then I was so interested in new society.  I invited my friend to be involved in this activity with the society.  So then we started changing this society.  We have _______ from industry-- Mitsubishi, Hitachi, Toshiba-- Oni Sensei [ph?].  At that time he was still-- I'm not sure-- PT student , as our youngest professor.  And Hiro , Fernando Darme [ph?] from Madrid and Andrew [ph?]-- do you know Andrew?  From Taiwan.  He's here.  He's a nice guy.  He's also a society president later on.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So how did you get to know these people?  At least some of them.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, the first three supported my laboratory.  That, or engineer.  High-position engineer.  Manager of  for electronics, motion control and microprocessor.  Then we changed the society.  It is 1990 or 1980.  We introduced the word mechatronics [ph?], robotics, informatics, and the memes [ph?].  So society was totally changed.  We created several societies,  Society, and this is the Robotics .  We cooperated with the computer society and the control system society and the industry society, and then we formed this new society and also we started  names.</interviewee>
<interviewer>While you were trying to change things, how did other people react?</interviewer>
<interviewee>We have a long, long discussion, overnight discussions and things like that.  And this is just a result, you know.  We have discussed so many things.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What were some other ideas, if you remember?</interviewer>
<interviewee>At that time we discussed about also some semiconductor device for control or something like that, and also communication technology.  Anyway, our decision was like this.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>And was Nikotronics [ph?] known at the time?  </interviewer>
<interviewee>Do you know the word Nikotronics was invented in Japan around 1970.  And, oh, most of the U.S. people are against that because this not an English word, he said.  And finally I think we voted whether or not we should use this word or not.  And we won.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What was the composition of the society at the time?  Were there a lot of Japanese members?</interviewer>
<interviewee>When I started, no Japanese-- only one.  And then these people came in, and they brought many people around them.  And when we started, members from outside the U.S. are the very few.  This time, I think the majority of members are from outside U.S.  Also European here,  and Fernando, and also  must be here.  Yeah.  He  he was involved in there.  So _______ must be here.  So European people came in, and also after Japanese, Korean and Taiwanese, from Singapore and the people following us.  And the _________ society.  This is my activity in ________ society.  This shot, this color shot, ________ in the U.S., the other in Japan.  So from this in 20 years and that, probably I mainly worked in the U.S.  This is  chief in Japan.  I started funding  electronics and also I worked as editor in chief of IE [ph?] Transaction.  And around year 2000 I came back to Japan, probably because I was too old-- I was around 60 years old.  Sixty years old is a very interesting age in Oriental countries.  In the old days, human life is 60 years.      So I came back and I served as the president of _________ Japan.  I was on Science Council of Japan member.  Oh, this the people around 2000: , Ren Ru [ph?], Toshio Fukuda [ph?].  Do you know ?  Passed away.  Kohe [ph?], Kazahiro [ph?].  All of them are out on here in this conference.  And we created this IROS conference in-- okay, probably it's here.  Around 2000 or 1990 through 2000 we started new transaction on mechatronics and Toshio and-- do you know Tomitsuka [ph?]-san?</interviewee>
<interviewer>No.</interviewer>
<interviewee>He's a professor at Berkeley here.  I met him three days ago.  He's the leader of controller engineering in California area,  Ren Ru.    Let me think.  He's the very last guy.  We also started informatics transaction, and Richard and  did it.  And also Toshio Fukuda start this IROS conference and Kobayashi Sensei started Rumen [ph?] Conference.  Do you know Rumen Conference.  And AI conference for Hideki.  I created conference for each person.  This a gift to him.</interviewee>
<interviewer>How do you go about creating a conference?</interviewer>
<interviewee>How do you what?</interviewee>
<interviewer>How do you create a conference?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh.  Good question.  Number one is you must be very top of some society, _________ society.  Otherwise you cannot make a proposal.  The second thing, if you have people like this, you can do that.  One is position.  This is very important thing.  And then anyway, if you find a good founder then that's okay.  And probably I gave chances to more than ten people, and then these, only five are surviving.  The other conference disappears.  They are successful, especially in IROS.  It was very successful.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>And so there must have been increasing interest in the field as well to support more conferences.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Right, that's right.  Right, that's right.  Exactly you are right.  That's a very important thing.  Yeah.  Oh, this is a very small one.  This is a citation index.  Number three, the IE [ph?] transaction.  Number one is signal processing-- I cannot see that.</interviewee>
<interviewer>It's a signal processing magazine.</interviewer>
<interviewee>And second is PIE [ph?].  They are not regular paper journal.  They are just for invited people.  So actually IE is the number one in regular transactions, and also mechatronics transactions are .  This is  something like that, over 300 or something like that.  So Japanese is good.  Anyway, we are very successful in this.  Important thing, except IE and mechatronics, other things are-- semiconductor or signal processing.  So this is very special cases.  Oh, friends.  We have New Year party at my house every year, on the first Saturday of the year.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>Some are sleeping.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, . </interviewee>
<interviewer>Oh, I see.  </interviewer>
<interviewee>And I think 30 percent come from outside Japan.    Oh, this is a picture of picture of, Ren Ru, myself, .  This is TJ Tarn.  Do you know TJ Tarn?  Washington University.  TJ Tarn, T-A-R-N.  He is Washington University in _________.  And he's a leader or robotics and the control in Chinese American society.  It's like a mafia.  He was here until yesterday.  He left.  And then Toshio.  And this is Kasuga-san [ph?].  This is Kasuga-san.  So some people come from Taiwan and Korea and China, I think even from Hungary or Germany or something like that.  We start this party 3 p.m. and the end is next day.  Next day.</interviewee>
<interviewer>That's a good party.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah, 30-40 people, and I think five dozen  beers and 10 bottles of scotch and 40 bottles of the wine.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>Wow.  Good job.</interviewer>
<interviewee>And my wife .</interviewee>
<interviewer>No wonder  was sleeping.</interviewer>
<interviewee>I'll give you this copy.  Oh, this is ITV [ph?] board of directors, 1990, 20 years ago.  I showed this picture because-- you see only two ladies, only two female.  This is 30 years after .  Incredible.  U.S. society now is diversity society, but still in some part of the society only two female, only one not white.  I was so disappointed by that at that time.  But situation in Japan is different.  All men.  This is year 2002.  I was the president of this society, .  No female.  No foreigners.  We have to improve our society.  Very ______.  This is board of directors last year.</interviewee>
<interviewer>There's one woman, two.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Only two.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Three.  There's one in the back.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Three?  How many not white?</interviewee>
<interviewer>One, two, three...  I'm stuck.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Four.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Five.  I think that five.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, six or seven.  It's improving, but still not enough.</interviewee>
<interviewer>But in 20 years--</interviewer>
<interviewee>Right, 20 years, a little bit improved.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Are there specific things that the directors and that you tried to do to make the situation improve?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes, continuously with the-- well, I was on the board  board I started to improve the situation, and then people agreed and then we started, but still slow.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What kinds of things did you do?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, I think if you read ________ in the bylaws, it's mentioned.  Probably it's on some part.  And bylaws or Actually…  Let me see.  On some document, yes.  Read some on the web.  And we believe a society without diversity cannot be so innovative.  The history shows that.  So we are much behind the U.S.  Very bad.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>And is this situation-- oh, that's 2002.  Okay.</interviewer>
<interviewee>This year only one. See, only one female, Uma. [ph?] This is a first in the history of this _______ society. Okay. This my team, research team. I'm here. I looked for your husband in the picture, but I cannot find it.</interviewee>
<interviewer>My dad? Really, he doesn't have a picture online?</interviewer>
<interviewee>After you've seen my computer.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Okay. I'll tell him to send you one.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay, okay, very good, and have his picture in, okay. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Oh, Shibata-san [ph?] in your lab as well? </interviewer>
<interviewee>He's-- </interviewee>
<interviewer>Because he studied with ________ right? </interviewer>
<interviewee>After PhD, he joined in my research group. I have a big fan, and I gave him a fan. This is Ren Drew, [ph?] this is Martin Burse, [ph?] ________ so oh, do you know him?  </interviewee>
<interviewer>Ah, Utkin. [ph?] </interviewer>
<interviewee>Vadel Utkin, [ph?] yeah. It's Richard. [ph?] Oh, this is ________ he-- I invited him to stay for one year as a visiting professor. </interviewee>
<interviewer>He's familiar, too. Was he in your lab at Tokyo Denki?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Right, exactly, exactly. _______ sensei yeah. And the problem, probably only two-- Uma is on here among 30 or 40.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So since there's so few women, even as students, in terms of the career, how does-- are there barriers to women, I mean, even in the US, they always talk about, you know, you get pregnant and then that's a different situation, or-- </interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay, number one thing is, anyway in engineering, women students are not only-- women students are very small. Some exceptions are computer science, also in architecture. And companies, industrial companies want to employ female researcher, because they like to develop a product with a women's feeling, so they need it, but very few women engineers want to go to industry. They want to be teacher, rather than go in a industry. Anyway, we have to change something. But it takes a long time for anything happen, having 1990-- during war, '95, Kobe earthquake. Japanese people do not trust civil and earthquake engineers after that. Nine-eleven-- after 9-11, I almost stopped visiting US, because, you know, travel in the US is not so comfortable . And I think this IRIS conference is only my exception I visit the US, so I propose them to have IRIS conference in the US, in Hawaii or in Las Vegas, and we do that. So that I can enjoy that. San Francisco is one of the good cities. And then, 1998, I moved from the University of Tokyo to Tokyo Metropolitan Institute, as the president. I was invited to be the president, and then. Do you know, the mayor of Tokyo, ________, very well known writer, novelist, and he invited me to be the president. He is a-- I don't like him in his philosophy, his rightist. But good friend, but I locked in the KIST after that. This was a very good experience for me. And I learn the Hangul. You know, Korean Hangul language grammar is the same, just the same as Japanese, but the writing are different, totally different and pronunciations are different. </interviewee>
<interviewer>So how was robotics in KIST in general, in Korea, different from Japan?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Growing very fast. And they have good students, PhD student, so probably taking a level of Korean, all of robotics are the same as the Japanese, and will grow up within a few years, because they have good people. Yesterday we decided to have this IRIS conference, in 20--?</interviewee>
<interviewer>Sixteen. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Sixteen, yes. </interviewee>
<interviewer>I mean, Korea seems-- I've never been to Korea, so I don't know what it looks like there, but just from talking to some of the Korean students, and reading some of the news, it seems to have taken the kind of initial Japanese promise of just really accelerated technological development, in a sense, even more seriously. Is that what it's actually like over there? I mean, they seem to be funding a lot of robotics projects for immediate application and--</interviewer>
<interviewee>Right, that's right. They are, you know, how do I say? They are very good in application over some technology or something like that, so they are complaining, no, we're not there, no one is there. And when I was here, I gave some talk for whole student, the whole-- and with professor, and somebody asked me, and this year, now we have Japanese, two or three robot project there. They asked me about why no Korean Nobel Prize. My answer was the KIST is a very good university, very high level, but no professor work in the Nobel Prize areas, basic physics, chemistry, biology or something like that. The only one Nobel Prize from Korea is past president, a peace here, Kim Dae-jung so my suggestion is Korea should work more on the basic science. And then they said, some of the professors said, you know, Korea is still developing stage, so they cannot afford to use people at the very basic sciences. I think it's not true. You know, Nobel Prize winners from Japan, started studying when we are very poor time, you know. So it's something they should-- something wrong. Okay, but the very good thing is-- oh, this is most well known TV stars, and my wife and I. I think that this is a summer-- synthesized picture. </interviewee>
<interviewer>They weren't standing right next to you? </interviewer>
<interviewee>Right. Oh, this is French. I organized that, it's actually a conference on robotics in the robotics area in Bordeaux. And the mayor of the city of Bordeaux, believed that this robotics could be a prior to now, a wine harvest or-- This one never the first thing there, so they are so happy, and they gave me some title of Wine Master.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Wow. </interviewer>
<interviewee>In some church. I was so happy then. </interviewee>
<interviewer>And hopefully lots of wine. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, a good customer. Oh, this another French award, national award. I supervised a French national project on the MEMS. One time in early 1990, the French and the delegate people came to Japan, and they go around the world trip, to investigate the MEMS technology, in the US, Germany, and Japan, and at that time, France was behind in this technology, and they decided to lock together with Japan. And I was on Japan's ________ so I-- we accepted almost 100 French engineers in our institute, Institute of Industrial Science, University of Tokyo. And we send out some of our PhD student to live together, and finally, they still going. This project is still going. They established a new national ________ on MEMS, and then they gave me some national award, Palme Academique. This award was established by Napoleon. So I think this is given by French--</interviewee>
<interviewer>You think it's the Prime Minister--</interviewer>
<interviewee>Prime Minister, Prime Minister. </interviewee>
<interviewer>For services to French culture.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Right. And they-- after I came back from Korea, I was elected President of Tokyo Tech University. This university has a long history, almost 100 years, and professors are very good, but I was disappointed, the quality of students was very bad. So I give up to improve this university. The professor and students must be almost the same level. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Why, why would they have that situation? It seems-- is the funding very good, or why would the really great professors want to be working?</interviewer>
<interviewee>The reason could be-- anyway, good students do not go to ________ area. And total number of-- trouble we have, in Japan, we have now over 700 universities. Among them, I think we have 200, more than 200 faculty ________ So many students, too many, so these are not very good students who go to University of Tokyo and any other university. They're-- they don't come to ________. Private university, very bad, so I give up. Then I join, again, I-- Tokyo Metropolitan University as the president. You know, at this time, city of Tokyo has now four universities. This is one of them, and then I proposed, the governor, to combine the four students into one, merge it into one, and then this university stopped. It started in 1995 and I was second president. This is a comprehensive university now. Just after I ________ the president of TMU, only two weeks later, I had a car accident, almost dead.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Oh no. </interviewer>
<interviewee>And my wife was driving, and I was the next, and our car stopped at a traffic jam, then end, then two ton truck hit from the back, at the speed of 100 kilometers per hour. And my wife and I, watching on the back mirror, so was prepared. But I was suddenly hit back, you know. I lost consciousness, and woke up in the hospital. My neck was injured. I still have some aftereffect. For example, my finger-- fingers don't work independently. This time okay, so I have some difficulty in typing. I started from a wheelchair, and I have ________ and the walking machine, and a stick, and standing up. It took six months.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Oh, very long time.</interviewer>
<interviewee>To recover, to get normal. It was a hard time. This is IRIS. Oh, I think it's not IRIS,  probably Ikara [ph?] I'm sure in Kobe, three years ago. Probably Ikara. Already drinking wine.</interviewee>
<interviewer>It doesn't hurt the recovery process.</interviewer>
<interviewee>And you know, my daughter said, I have some pain in the neck, then you know, some medicine or alcohol? </interviewee>
<interviewer>One of the other, not both. </interviewer>
<interviewee>That's right. So I chose alcohol. </interviewee>
<interviewer>It's tastier. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Right. Oh, this is-- ________ in this area trying some other thing, it's a special issue, only professor Fumio Harashima for-- can't see that. Celebrating his contribution in robotics and mechatronics, yeah. </interviewee>
<interviewer>It's June, 2010. </interviewer>
<interviewee>And this picture, my wife took this picture. No one, in such a case, you know, professor sits on a table, and on the books behind.</interviewee>
<interviewer>You look much more relaxed. It's better.</interviewer>
<interviewee>This is a well known place. This is ________ this is a very special geographical structure. This is close to Kyoto, and my wife and I went to this place just for taking this picture. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Well then it's good they put it on the magazine, so everybody can see. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Right, exactly. This year, and this is followed by ________ still going, and people do not trust science and technology anymore. This is a human accident. I know-- as you know, I was a president of ________ and at that time, I was already critical to a nuclear power, and I write some articles several times on criticizing nuclear power, but I know, I'm very sorry. I did not take any strong action, I did not start any strong action. I feel guilty of that. So 20 kilometers, 30 kilometers, I think we cannot-- people cannot come back into this area for the next half century. It's like on Chernobyl, more than that. Radiation is more than that. </interviewee>
<interviewer>So how has that changed now, the discussion about science and technology. In the beginning when you started, it was very positive, and it was seen as a potential kind of way to save and improve society. How is the discussion different now? </interviewer>
<interviewee>I think, and as I told you now, people are already rich. You know, it's a mature society, so they are expecting, you know, home appliances and the cars and something like that. Number of car production in Japan are going down, and semiconductors are going down, and the computer is also going down, and our science and technology are going to the direction of, biotechnology or medicare technology, and also some anti-earthquake technology. Most serious problem is we are losing our bright students, young students, so we have to import. Like the US, but our problem is, you know, it is difficult for foreign people to be happy in Japanese society because of some culture difference, you know. You know from Europe and the US, is originally the same cultural-- the same culture, so their happiness is compatible. But Japanese people and western people are different, totally different, so you know, they come to Japan, but they cannot be happy here. And Japanese people in general, cannot be happy in a western country. But why-- Chinese people and people from India come from the US-- totally different culture, but they can be happy, because here is extreme poor. That's a big difference, you know. And another thing, why people from Korea and China, don't come to Japan? Still aftereffect of the war. You know, China Japan is something like a past, like German, France issue, something like that, but Germany and France is now changes, they are very close. You know for the last 30 years, they exchange young people, high school student, starting there. But unfortunately in Asia, in the far east Asia, we didn't have such a policy. Still, you know, personally we're friends, but as a group, they are conflicting each other, it's very bad. Probably we are guilty for that, I'm sure. This is another history. Home appliance in my family. This is-- you know, 1948, just after the war, radio, vacuum tube radio. I watched this radio now so carefully, and from the back, and I've seen that. Telephone, tape recorder, washing machine, refrigerator, transistor radio. These are Sonys, and TV, black and white, car, the first car. I was married here, I was married here.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Oh, when you got the car? </interviewer>
<interviewee>Just after. Yeah, and the cassette tape recorder and air conditioner, color TV, microwave oven, okay. From here, you know, this are not-- that one is traditional home appliance. From here, everything is, you know, computer based. In 1974, the first microprocessor came out, and ________ from ten years, '70 to '84, we didn't buy any. It's already there. Some time, it's already there. And the new stuff, new kind of stuff is here, Nintendos and TV game, microprocessor, word processor from Toshiba, ________ MS DOS, Windows 3.5. And the internet, 9.8 kilobit, do you remember that? </interviewee>
<interviewer>Not really, I was too small. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Probably you were small then. And Windows 95, and the digital camera, mobile telephone, you know, ISDN, ________ TV, ________ DVD, car, I got a new car, Lexus, these are mostly electronic, not mechanical, you know, electronic product, navigator, wireless route, fiber, optical fiber came to my home. It's a car, this Nintendo's Wii, do you know Wii?</interviewee>
<interviewer>Mm-hmm. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay, this the last one. But this year, I bought an iPad. I enjoy it. This is the history of my family, very interesting. </interviewee>
<interviewer>And how do you think that in terms of, you know, robotics or science and technology, how is-- do you see kind of a similar change in the type of research or type of questions that people are dealing with? </interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, robotics is-- the robot industry is very similar, as you know. We introduced a robot into the manufacturing process in the middle of '90-- probably the beginning of 1980, and then this is-- we introduced robot in place of the human workers, and the machine is the same. That is the reason why robot is human-like, mechanically, but at the time, no intelligence on that robot, just the replacement of the human worker, mechanical replacement, you know. And then from 1990, you know, certainly we developed an intelligent robot, but at that time we redesigned the whole manufacturing plant, then we don't need the robot. The whole manufacturing plant is robot-like, we don't like the human-like, mechanical human-like on the machine. So robot are getting out from the manufacturing. And then they lost their job there. So we introduced them-- we tried to introduce them into houses, human houses, but still the market is very small. But observing this robotics from other aspect, you know, robotics is not an industry, this is a basic engineering, and so ideal, and the philosophy of the robotics is applied to every-- almost everywhere industry, that's enough. So robotics it serves industry is very small, but it is very important research subject, so I think that we expect the bright student coming to robotics and go to other-- working now, automobile, and aircraft, or even on nanotechnology, you know, we need nanorobotics for the manipulation of a single molecule, and so robotics is a very basic-- it's a regular-- it's magnetic theory, or ________ theory or control theory or something like that. It's not an industry itself.</interviewee>
<interviewer>But even in Japan it seems like the focus is very much on trying to find specific applications, and then there's a lot of disappointment when robots, as you know, just a robot, aren't able to be applied in society. So-- but you seem to be pointing out that it's actually something different, that it's much more kind of a-- not a basic science, but practically on that level.</interviewer>
<interviewee>People ________ but for now, for us it is a basic technology, and probably within ten years, robot will come into houses for, you know, nothing, nothing, or to help aged people, you know, for working or taking bath or something like that. I think that would be the largest application. Certainly we have some cleaning robots, but it's a small thing, you know.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Do you have one?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh yeah.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Okay. It's not on there.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, it's not here.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>It's not Roomba, is there a Japanese version?</interviewer>
<interviewee>No. Sure, Toshiba. We think such a robot is not-- it's like a toy. Yeah, not so interesting.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Not a serious appliance yet. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Right, that's right. Okay, let's go. Anyway, this is almost a history of Japan, you know, the Japanese technology, history of Japanese technology. Okay, my comment on that, something a joke, don't take it seriously. This transparence I made, is 30 years ago, we had-- we started a project with the institute, and then we go to this ________ or something like that, we go to panic, and feel guilty, and we punish some innocent guy. And when the project is over, we give praise and honor for the non-participant. This is a typical Japanese research project. </interviewee>
<interviewer>So you do this over and over again. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Right. Something we can-- on the PowerPoint more beautifully, but this is a transparency at that time, I made this copy. This is sort of my experience, you know. Okay, so I go to--</interviewee>
<interviewer>These are the awards you got for not participating. </interviewer>
<interviewee>That's right, exactly, this is an example. This is an example. This has-- first, this part is award for one paper, a single project. The middle one is for the last ten years activity. And this is the whole life honor. People say, if you received this kind of an award, you can get out. The end of the life. </interviewee>
<interviewer>You're done.</interviewer>
<interviewee>This is the end of life, the middle of the life, beginning. </interviewee>
<interviewer>We're in the 2010s now though, so what kind of award are you going to get next?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah, it's a dangerous honor. Okay, next joke. Oh, then I create several fellowship awards. Now this is IRIS award. This is IRIS award. And this is-- I wrote-- this is mainly in Europe. This is in Korea. The reason why this award was established is I was very much paid by KIST, incredible amount of salary, so my wife and I, do there, and a very good life, but still a big amount of money left in won, Korean won, and my wife advised me, do not take Korean won into Japan. So I donate it, whole thing, whole money to Academic Society of Korea, and then they establish a Fumio Harashima award. So I like this award, and actually it's my wife's award. </interviewee>
<interviewer>So they should have put her name on it. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh yes.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Or both of your names or something. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah, okay.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Tell them.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay, you know, two are different, and next month we go to Korea for presenting this award. Okay, I'll change. </interviewee>
<interviewer>She'll be happy.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Very good, very happy in that, okay. This award is presented on Thursday at an old luncheon. Yeah, probably I will do that. Look at this. </interviewee>
<interviewer>I'm here. </interviewer>
<interviewee>I was appointed as a professor-- </interviewee>
<interviewer>In the no money stage.</interviewer>
<interviewee>No money. An the beginning, a graduate student with me. No money, no time, no brain, no body, no body power, and now I'm 70. </interviewee>
<interviewer>I think, enjoy should be in there. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Good, I'll change this around.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Enjoy what you have. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, very good.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Don't worry about-- no-- </interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay, this is my experience, my history as a professor.</interviewee>
<interviewer>It's good to know what to look forward to.</interviewer>
<interviewee>So you study here?</interviewee>
<interviewer>Yes.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Long way.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Yes, very long way.</interviewer>
<interviewer>I'm getting here slowly.  I still have little money, but the no time is slowly happening.</interviewer>
<interviewee>This time 40s are not very hard.  You are very busy in university jobs and also family leisure.  Extremely busy.  No time.  And so exhausted and then 50s are no brain, but in other word in 50s you have time, money, and students.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So they have the brains and they can take care of it.</interviewer>
<interviewee>That's right.  You don't have to have a brain.</interviewee>
<interviewer>It's good to know.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah, this is _______ of the end.  Thank you.</interviewee>
<interviewer>I have one question for you which may take a little bit, but going way back to the slide where you had your research, I was wondering if you could kind of just lead us through some of the different kinds of projects and robots you worked on and the kind of concepts that you think are important with that one.</interviewer>
<interviewee>I started from control and that-- one of the applications I was interested in motion control.  At this time we did not have any microprocessor, no computer.  We use an analog circuit so it's impossible to develop a robot at that time.  Microprocessor came out here at this 9975 out here from Intel.</interviewee>
<interviewer>I think Inoue Sensei was showing we were at ISRR, but he was showing some very early things that they did before with analog.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Right.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Yeah.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Right.  So exhausting job, yeah.  Incredible thing at the time.  On that anyway he did get started this project in my lab.  Many critical _______ robot system control like _______ also came into our group and _______ intelligence group, this is a government project and I think over _______ year one billion yen and--</interviewee>
<interviewer>So that's--</interviewer>
<interviewee>Ten million.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Yeah.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Dollar and we formed a research group from young researcher from throughout the world, throughout Japan and they work his own place.  We communicate every day through internet and every three or four month we get physical get-together to exchange idea and something there and Shibata [ph?] was one of them and we-- I think this is more than ten years ago, almost ten years ago.  At that time they are early 30 or something like that.  They are reading professors.  Most of them.  So we-- some of them in computer sciences and some of them from mechanical control and the other is a psychology because we need interaction.  The basic idea of this project is we understand-- thinking about an interaction between a human and a computer and a mechanical machine.  We understand the computer, how the computer works, how can the mechanical ______ works, but they don't understand human.  This is a mismatching on a coexistence.  For example probably this is not a good example in the U.S. _______ in the Japanese we can say my wife and I have been married for over 40 years.  We don't talk a lot.  We just don't understand easily just a very simple behavior or doing nothing.  Just watching a face.  For example, if we get up she was in my face.  Look at the weather.  Then she decide what kind of coffee is the best for me.  Yeah.  No conversations here.  So the interaction must be like this.  So we-- this technology-- the goal of this technology, computer side understand the human psychology.  It's a _____________ is one of the good example.  How this animal understand human customer for example and we have been successful in this in some sense just we start a similar thing.  Another example is we try to connect our human brain to the computer, but this caused some ethical issue here.  We should not do that.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What were the issues?</interviewer>
<interviewee>For example, when you have a baby put  into here in a fixed number then this baby can use it forever.  Do you think it's a good thing or not?</interviewee>
<interviewer>Mm-mm.</interviewer>
<interviewee>No, probably not.  This something like that.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Oh so it was meant to be kind of a permanent connection to the robot?  Okay.  Not just okay for ten minutes we're going to-- okay.</interviewer>
<interviewer>Implanting it, yeah.</interviewer>
<interviewee>That's right.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Okay.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Probably we have the society, whole society should discuss over the issue.  Gives you more time.  Take me there.  This is impossible.  But we stopped it.</interviewee>
<interviewer>But there also seems to be a issue with how people understand robots, so engineers understand computers very well, but the typical user and I think in Japan there is talk about elderly or children or different people who might be sick.  They don't necessarily understand what's going on.</interviewer>
<interviewee>No, they don't have to understand the details inside electronic or not.  That's only if they are after some training they understand what the thinking about and another thing-- how do you say?  This project include another research in the area that is human adaptive  is machine adapt itself to human.  Normally we must adapt ourselves to machine by training, so this idea is a training the mechanics automatic adapting to a human.  This is the second stage of this.  This project is the second.  This is also government funded  this project.  At this project I was a  university and I followed this project and ______ professor were _______ university are good, but the _______ are very poor so this-- unfortunately this project wasn't so successful because you need a good student, young and _______ student while carrying out this sort of project.  This is bad.  So many thing.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>So what were some of the kind of important robots or projects, applications that came out of some of these projects?</interviewer>
<interviewee>_________?</interviewee>
<interviewer>So what were some of the-- if you were going to pick just a few kind of example like robot projects that you worked on or results that you had with some of these.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh yeah.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What would they be?</interviewer>
<interviewee>At this time my technology was used to machine tool control was even a _______ or another way _______ and then motion control-- oh, I forgot to tell you an important thing.  In the middle of 1975 I met on a topic set  [ph?] with Toyota.  We draw together at the ginza, a nice crowd, and  this existed [ph?] number two and number three over on Toyota.  He said Toyota will give you any amount of my research fund so I asked back.  I am not a automobile engineer so I don't know if _______ anymore, but he said at the time he said after 30 years from this time electronics will be the major technology over automobile industry.  He said incredible this 40 years ago he said and it's actually happened and so my robot team was not 100 percent supported by Toyota.  Also Toshiba was a supporter and _______ as a baby we started developing hybrid cars here.  Can you imagine that?  Forty years ago Toyota and I joined that group and they are almost in the mechanical engineers.  I mean 20-some years ago who we worked together to make kind of concept of hybrid cars at the time and it's commercialized here for 30 years and 40 years after.  This is the biggest thing which I achieved.  Still so Toyota top executives are very familiar to each other.  They still think together.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So what kind of things did you build for Toyota?</interviewer>
<interviewee>On hybrid cars?</interviewee>
<interviewer>Yeah.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, 1975 is a special year is a fossil oil crisis, another crisis and Toyota worried about in the future in a few years, so they started on several concept cars.  One of them is a hybrid car and other time we still we don't have a computer so it's very difficult to control engine and motors and batteries.  It's energy flow [ph?] and the most important on this subject to the long-life battery.  The second is the connection mechanical and electrical.  This is a _______ technology and in control _______ and another time we put in the batteries, engines, motor, it took too long.  This power train is too long so we made a very long car  batteries like this  and then we-- one time we give up using a gas engine car internal combustion car and one time we use a external combustion car engine like on a gas turbine or something like that, but the gas turbine, the rotation speeds are too high, so we needed to control that.  So many trial and error, and finally Prius was born.  It's a long history and also is a-- this-- I did not show this story because it's a something of a secret for Toyota.  How is the hybrid cars was in the develop _________.  It's a secret, you know.  So it cannot officially open and this _______ a little more supported by Toshiba and--</interviewee>
<interviewer>So more from the manipulator robot human adaptive.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Right, right.  Toshiba, I think when you are in Tokyo Toshiba people are always staying  and are fully supportive for this project and so Tomizosan [ph?]  invited he _____ Toshiba's money also _________ from Taiwan.  Even _________.  __________ he was a visiting professor supported by Toshiba, so they are called Toshiba professors.   and also Joe Mua [ph?] from Australia.  Probably one more .  Some European I thought.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>So what does Toshiba, do you know, expect if it's not secret, expect to do with the human adaptive-- yeah.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Probably for home appliances future.  It's just a basic technology.  They, Toshiba as a manufacturer can apply this technology to any home appliance.  Home appliances are always in human use, so human machine interaction is a key thing for Toshiba.  See Toshiba is a leader in this area.  Panasonic is also.  Sony is okay.  So my life, many thing happened incredible.  I was born 1940 and the end of the war is in 1945 and in July just one month before the end of the war we had air bomb by U.S. and my whole town completely destroyed and we-- fortunately the whole family survived.  Many people died around me and this was probably very shocking for me and I my last memory before that so I cannot-- unbelievable.  I cannot _______ today we can enjoy such a beautiful life.  Probably I'm afraid you and your family have such a similar experience.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Yeah, we just weren't actually there because we were in Japan when the war started so then we stayed there.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh yeah.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Yeah. </interviewer>
<interviewee>You were outside the country.</interviewee>
<interviewer>We were accidentally.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh accidentally?</interviewee>
<interviewer>Yeah.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Here in the Ropongi area.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Right.  No, actually that was when we were with Onishi Sensei [ph?].</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oni Sensei, oh--</interviewee>
<interviewer>Yes because my dad was doing the one year sabbatical and then we went to Fukuoka for a year.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Right.  Very happy.  Oh so you know Fukuoka?</interviewee>
<interviewer>We were very lucky.  Yes, yes.  I went to Fukuoka International School.</interviewer>
<interviewee>I was born there, yeah.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Yeah, so we only knew it from talking to family.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay and _______ some secrets.  __________ started 1974 the story here is official.  Some secret is before 1974 when I was a teaching student I thnk transaction is a very wonderful thing, publishing in the paper there.  I read some of the papers in the library.  We could not afford to join because when I do is very hard and probably the first time I published the papers _________ actually the Ph.D. Thursdays or another then two or three.  Then sometime before that my submission, submitted papers were rejected and other time we did not have internet so it takes a long time to for by airmail correspondence.  So I felt irritated.  So what I decided is to take over the whole society  then I would be able to easy to publish paper.</interviewee>
<interviewer>That's a good plan.</interviewer>
<interviewer>I should just take over.</interviewer>
<interviewee>A lot of people laughed, but I was serious and I did it.  This isn't a second story-- this is official story.</interviewee>
<interviewer>How do you plan to take over?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay.  I did not intend it but what I did and the results, what I did is I attended every meeting of this society.  The other people in-- one time the other time _______ then I know whole thing of the society so no other people can manage this society.</interviewee>
<interviewer>The knowledge.</interviewer>
<interviewee>And as a result I was elected the president and probably I am the first to not ________ America to be society president that is from outside the U.S.  What happen is we have a someone coalition [ph?] so somebody ask me where do you live?  I live in Tokyo.  For what?   So I was-- I'm a Japanese and I live in Tokyo.  I'm a professor _______ you know at the university of Tokyo. And I live in Tokyo.</interviewee>
<interviewee>So I said I joked.  I am professor of _______ Tokyo.  In short this is called IUFT.</interviewee>
<interviewee>University _________ of Tokyo.  Somebody not believe. U.S. people are so nice people.  They don't feel any border of the country or something, a geographical thing.</interviewee>
<interviewer>I guess you can call that nice.</interviewer>
<interviewee>So I loved it.</interviewee>
<interviewee>So I like U.S. very much and I love many thing diverse _______ a number one issue ___________ which I learn from the U.S.  Most important thing, and I have been watching in the U.S. society since the end of 1961 or late ‘70s.  The society has been changing after the civil war started.  I was so impressed by that and comparing the U.S. and Japan, they do not recognize this problem until probably ten years ago and ten years ago we stop it.  It's a big difference in our two countries.  So now at the present of Tokyo _______ University I stopped last year.  My main subject at this university is diversity.  I said that and we formed some committee and _______ and we started and last month-- no, in July this year we decided to employ-- we employ a new professor and we decide attrition 30 percent over newly employed professor must be female.  Now in a total professors only five percent  so a new professor must be in 30 percent or female.  We decide so now whole university in a panic  that we'll do that.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>So if I want to move to Japan I should just do it now.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh yeah.  Sure.</interviewee>
<interviewee>Okay.  Female and 49.  It's a __________.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Great.</interviewer>
<interviewer>I'll start getting my university panicked straight away.</interviewer>
<interviewer>Great.  I don't know if you want to add anything else or--</interviewer>
<interviewee>No thank you.  Any other question I'm happy to answer.</interviewee>
<interviewer>We have a quick one.  We want to put a little education part.  So this is going to go on the website for IEEE and we want to have a little part for education for students who are interested in robotics so would you have any advice for young people who are interested in getting into robotics?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Robotics.  Robotics is in general it is a-- you think about robotics is part of engineering, but my feeling is as I told you interaction between human and machine is robotics.  Now exact-- okay.  I can't give an exact definition of robot.  Robot is a machine.  It must be mechanical and sense the environment and then based on this information from environ take action to the environment over to other people.  That is a definition of a robot.  So the shape is not necessary human, right, and so the robotics study must include certainly mechanical engineering, electronics and the computer science and must include the psychology to understand the human behavior and then also some sociology.  So occasional robotics must cover wider disciplines.  So recently even in the U.S. university level education for some persons becomes narrower and narrower and in the old days undergraduate education in the USA universities were liberal art based, but it's changing.  MIT is a typically change.  They are a very small area at undergraduate.  _____________ I think are still liberal arts label [ph?].  I think most of the U.S. university used to be liberal arts label, that is changing.  So they should go back to liberal art just for robotics.  If you have us on a broad background to make them a good researcher in robotics.  Only mechanical, only narrow computer science, I think you may make a ___________ narrow.  So criticize to the U.S. robot is a U.S. robodics research is mainly funded by DOD.  So anyway DOD research is to kill people.  The goal is to kill people.  This is very bad.  Korean robot researches something like that ___________ geographical geopolitical situation.  But, researchers in Japan is completely free from defense technology.  So in the sense we Japanese robotics engineers are very, very proud of that.  We are the only research group which is totally free from the military research.  This is-- I'm sorry I criticize some of the U.S. and China, and probably you know in Nevada City they have some Middle East-like town for training of robot battle war.  Technically this is very interesting research for robotics engineer, but this is ethical issue.  We never accept another research fund from DOD Japan.  This is not the rule, but our own decision and even if it was very attractive subject and attracted to big fund, we already reject that, because of the ___________.  Our life started like that.  We still remember that.  The young people-- I don't know how young people think about that.  Still so far we are leaders of this in the Japanese engineer so in a sense we have been keeping a distance _______ issue ___________.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Do you think it'll become more difficult now that I mean there was a lot of promise about human robotics verges the general market and there was before the industrial robot market, but the general human market is not so easy to develop technology for, so do you think that maybe there will be more military applications as-- or no?</interviewer>
<interviewee>In general government pay a big amount of fund to _______ for human-- human robot interaction is probably applications start from handicapped people.  In general handicapped people are poor so they cannot afford to buy such a expensive machine, so I believe government must support this kind of project.  Otherwise this kind of project cannot be developed without big fund.  So I suggest-- no, I don't have a strong power, but anyway I suggested government, some section of government to support this robot for handicapped people in place of a military robot.  You don't have to use big money for military.  Use the money for this.  Otherwise it cannot be done on a commercial basis.  Medical care and surgery, something like that.  This kind of technology can be developed commercial basis because some patients are very rich.  But in general, handicapped people are poor.  They don't have a good profession and jobs.  That's the problem.  So medical robot is okay.  Any other?</interviewee>
<interviewer>This is really good.  I think that is good advice.</interviewer>
<interviewee>So how common in U.S. societies you know,  Medical technology in the U.S. is the best in the world for rich people, but in general Medicare system is the worst in the world it's among the wealthy countries and for us Japanese that's such a U.S. situation is very good.  U.S. developed high tech Medicare system __________ very good situation for us.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>Great.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Thank you.  I think yes we asked and answered everything.</interviewer>
</interview>
</subject>
