<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<subject>
<name>Kazuhiro Kosuge</name>
<interview>
<interviewer>So if you could start by telling us your name and where and when you were born?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Uh-hum. I am Kazuhiro Kosuge. I was born in Japan  in 1955 and yeah, actually I was born in Tsu [ph?] City which is located in Mie [ph?] prefecture. This is adjacent to Aichi [ph?] prefecture.  Aichi prefecture the main city is Nagoya City so you may know where it is. That's okay?</interviewee>
<interviewer>Where did you start at school?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Actually I was graduated from Tokyo Institute of Technology and my career is a little bit different from other professors in Japan. After finishing master course there I entered the Nippon Denso, one of the Toyota ______ companies and now it's called DENSO. And Denso means electrical equipment for automobiles. So they are now I think one of the largest companies in the world concerned with the electrical equipment for automobiles. And I worked there for two years and three months and then I graduated from the company. I went back to the again the original previous laboratory at Tokyo Tokyo Tech and Department of Control Engineering and after that I joined a laboratory as a Research Associate and when I became a Research Associate Japanese we have a little bit different Japanese system which means that I could become Research Associate without having PhD degree. And then I was working as a Research Associate and doing some research I got the PhD there. And after that it took about eight years for me because I was working during the day time and so my time for research was a little bit limited, but I learned a lot. And then I became I first I visited the United States for one year. I was with Harry Sutter [ph?] and he hosted me at the Mechanical Engineering Department and I learned a lot from him. And then I joined Nagoya University Toshio [ph?] _______ lab as an Associate Professor and stayed there four years and a half, and them I moved to Tohoku University and joined one of the departments relating to Mechanical Engineering and became a professor. So I became a professor at the age of 39 years old and the main reason why I moved is that I like to have do something by myself and that is a kind of a reason why I moved, I changed my job many times. </interviewee>
<interviewer>So your degrees were in Control Engineering?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Control Engineering, yes. And actually my supervisor at the Tokyo Tech was a professor Furuta, Katsuhisa Furuta; he is now serving as the President of our Tokyo Denki University and he is still very active in the field and he is one of the pioneers in the area of control theory in Japan and so I learned a lot in some sense, and the education which I received from his lab is really, really valuable for me. I learned a kind of a basic fundamentals concerned with control theory, how to develop the theoretical work and a very interesting thing, maybe this is a kind of a joke. Furuta means old rice field, okay? And Asada [ph?] means shallow [ph?] rice field. Fikuda [ph?] means fortune rice field.  And after having served four years and a half I got fortune and become a professor at the Tohoku University. Yeah, that is my career. </interviewee>
<interviewer>So there's all the rice fields. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah, I have to cultivate it by myself and that is what I'm doing now. </interviewee>
<interviewer>What was your thesis project?</interviewer>
<interviewee>For the PhD it's a control theory. I built up in some sense I forgot the name. At the time I was interested in nonlinear control theory and my work is a kind of a generalization [ph?] for a class of nonlinear systems by utilizing a nonlinear fieldwork. That is my master thesis. Based on that we proposed a kind of a model following controller for the linear system and together with the generalization brought by nonlinear field work we made a kind of a robust controller which could control the manipulator based on the many different types of sensory information. And that is still I mean I'm still using the results of my PhD thesis for the kind current work. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Which manipulators were you using at the time?</interviewer>
<interviewee>At the time, actually it was a long time ago. First manipulator which I used is the I tried to remember, yes, it's a kind of a prototype manipulator developed by one company that we had a collaboration with the company and they developed a manipulator and so we designed a controller. Other time still we don't have our first computer system and we used Nova [ph?] from Data General [ph?] and it is really, really slow.  And memory size was at the beginning 32 kilobytes and then it extended to finally 128 kilobytes. And so the memory is very limited so we made our own assembly language and our own 14 [ph?] point computation system by ourselves so that we could increase the computational speed. And so I still remember that we tried to increase the computational speed but maximum sampling rate was which we could attain is around I think sampling rate maybe along 30 hertz [ph?] or something like that. It was very, very slow. And then after that, that is a time when I first direct drive manipulator was introduced invented by Harry Sutter as well as Professor Takyo Kanaday [ph?] the group at CMU and later in some sense we received several direct drive motors from a company and by utilizing that we did several experiments using 2D or 3D planer manipulator system and we did our first control as well as dual-manipulator [ph?] coordinated motion control digital [ph?] manipulators using only on the plane, horizontal manipulators. And then we had another collaboration with an industrial company and we tried, we implemented our control scheme in that industrial robots and we did several experiments. After that we had another collaboration with the industrial robot maker and manufacturer and I think at that time we extended our planar results into real 3D space. So by utilizing two six degrees of freedom manipulator, we developed our single master multiservice systems. Single master means we developed two joysticks. Each have three degrees of freedom so the total six degrees of freedom master manipulator could control the twelve degrees of freedom, two industrial robots. And I think that is one of the hardest work relating to the coordinated motion control dual [ph?] manipulators using real industry robots. Other time as long as I know only two or three groups are doing this similar work except us. One is Osamakative's [ph?] work and another one is there is one group in Montpelier, France, Pierre Dorshe's [ph?] group was doing that and I think by thru the real experiments using real industry robots we learned a lot and we are confident that our system works with the 4D [ph?] could be applied to 4D real [ph?] applications. </interviewee>
<interviewer>What year was that and what kind of robots were you using?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Pardon?</interviewee>
<interviewer>What year was that?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah many years ago. It was just before I visit the United States for one year so I think it was 1988 or 1989. Yes, I joined M.I.T. 1989 so I think 1988. And it's many years ago. </interviewee>
<interviewer>What companies' robots?</interviewer>
<interviewee>That was supported by Nachifuji Kogi [ph?] Company and at the time we had a friend there. Later he moved to another company so I don't want to embarass his name. It is a kind of secret. Now he is-- actually this is confidential but the guy who supported our research at Nachifuji Kogi company is now a kind of what I say one of our I think I don't know how you call it in-- one of the managers Fanuk [ph?] so this part is confidential in some sense. </interviewee>
<interviewer>The whole funded part, we won't. </interviewer>
<interviewee>And also of course I had to implement a control scheme at that time. We need a high speed computational system, okay? We had a very good relation at the time with Sony. We have several friends. One day Sony's guy visited us and he said that they said that they are willing to provide us with a new servo controller system. Servo amplifiers, server controller systems and each controller could control two axis, two motors. But I told them I am not interested in that joined control systems. We are interested in kind of what to say, a total control so we'd like to control a 360 axis. It was interesting. At that time Sony looks very, very in some sense very active and they are interested in my idea so they told me that they are going to develop a kind of a customized computer system. It's called a beta [ph?] slicer [ph?] system so by putting a lot of chips they can develop kind of their own control C.P.U.s. So they developed the C.P.U. computational system consist of two floating point systems, two F.P.U.s, and one A.L.U. [ph?], and several memories or something and the length of the micro-assembler. I forgot the name precisely. The _______ is 128 bits. It was really, really powerful. And after that I was Japanese, I am Japanese, so we couldn't know how to give a presentation concerned with this special processor. A similar work was presented in the United States. They call it a very long word instruction-something [ph?]. So I think if we knew how to present it, how to publish the results and maybe it could attract some people. But it's very powerful and it has a capability of a floating point, a computation of maybe at that time 20 megaflops. So now of course now the C.P.s are very, very the performance is very high and 20 megaflops is almost nothing. But at that time it's amazing C.P.U. so by utilizing a C.P.U. and together with the Nachifuji Kogi's robots ________ system we could realize a single master multi-service systems. </interviewee>
<interviewer>You mentioned that you have a lot of friends in industry. How did you meet these friends or how did you make these connections? </interviewer>
<interviewee>Connections? Oh, that's a good question. When I was at the time I was with Tokyo Tech, Tokyo Institute of Technology and of course it's located inside of the Tokyo area and so many people are coming. And actually probably partially they are interested in my research. And partially they would like to support my research. And I have a lot of networks and based on the network I am still doing some collaborative research based on the network which I established I mean when I was at Tokyo Tech. </interviewee>
<interviewer>So people were generally visiting Tokyo Tech and then they would also come see your work?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah, because Tokyo is very convenient so as long as we are doing something interesting they can easily I mean visit us and of course my boss at the time Professor Furuta was a well-known professor in the field of control engineering so actually, they are interested in that. </interviewee>
<interviewer>What was the first robot you worked on? </interviewer>
<interviewee>First robot? First robot is manipulator as I mentioned but developed by a company and it's a kind of _____ collaborate research. And they thought that maybe the application at the time control theory is a kind of is called a modern control theory and so they considered that by applying an advanced control theory they could I mean improve the performance of their own robots. But actually we couldn't do it because of kind of a computational burden [ph?]. The computer system was so slow to implement our own controllers. </interviewee>
<interviewer>These were projects that you still did while you were at Tokyo Institute of Technology?</interviewer>
<interviewee>No, no, no, no. Now I've already spent 18 years at the Tohoku University and I have my own network and a part with the network is relating to the network of the kind-- which I established or created during my-- yeah. </interviewee>
<interviewer>When did you first engage the international community of robotics? </interviewer>
<interviewee>International community of robotics? When I was young I was a Research Associate, at the beginning of course I have nothing to present. And after that, it's interesting that at that time linear control theory in some sense theoretical work had been saturated at that time so my supervisor, Professor Furuta, recommended me to do something in the robotics field because at that time robotics is kind of emerging field for the control people so first I start-- yeah, the reason why I started the robotics research. And _____ Furuta ___ itself and they are also doing a lot of research like one is at the time the largest project was is concerned with the to develop our own computer design system for the CAD for the control system design. And so I am the only one guy who is doing robotics in that lab and that was really good for me because everything, I have to do everything by myself. And nobody knows. Nobody has knowledge concerned with robots so I did everything by myself and that's why it took a long time to get the PhD. </interviewee>
<interviewer>When you first got your appointment as an Associate Professor were you working on robots then or were you working on multiple areas? </interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay, Toshiro's [ph?] field is really, really wide. At that time he when his laboratory he just started micro-machine stuff. Probably at the beginning he was expecting that I was involved in micromechanical system, MEMS, Micro Electrical Mechanical Systems, but unfortunately I had in some sense I had a lot at the time in other fields. So I was involved in both and also so I learned a lot and when I was at Tokyo Tech in some sense I did kind of my research field a little bit limited. And after joining Toshiro's group, he is doing a lot of things of course so I have to take care of students, we have to take care of students and each student has his or her own area. So that helps me a lot to learn a lot of different things and how to in some sense how to develop the kind of supposed that you have to do something different. Also in research as long as you are doing research you have to do something different. And so I learned how to in some sense how to supervise students so that he or she could do something different in that field. And that's a good experience, very, very good experience for me. </interviewee>
<interviewer>What were some of the projects that you remember from that time?</interviewer>
<interviewee>At the time I think that really a lot. And also my previous sponsor [ph?] at Tokyo Tech gave me two robots with different controllers. And by utilizing the system I continued the research of the dual-run [ph?] system. And that is one of my field. Another one is that by utilizing the manipulator in some sense we developed a kind of a human augmentation, power augmentation system and it's a kind of human-robot interaction, physical human-robot interaction system and I think that still continues in some sense. My most of well-known robots in Tohoku University is the Dance Partner Robot. It has physical human level interaction and the idea came from my experience at Nagoya University concerned with the human power augmentation system. And we developed a very robust and stable controller for the power augmentation. Supposed to like to amplify human's power by utilizing mechanical system then the system interacts with the environment and the system robot interacts with the human, okay? So in order to assure the stability of the system the stability of the system depends on the human dynamics as well as the environment dynamics. So what we did is that by controlling a dynamics of the mechanical system so that it has a kind of it behaves like a tool, a passive tool then we can make sure that the total system is stable. And the stability doesn't depend on the human dynamics as well as the environment dynamics. And that is the idea which we developed at the time and it still works very well. </interviewee>
<interviewer>The application would be for exoskeletons?</interviewer>
<interviewee>But unfortunately  Japan is a kind of over in some sense too much likes too much regulation concerned with the safetyness [sic] of robots and so we couldn't bring the technology into the real environment. After that, we are still searching for that in some fields in the future we can apply the technology.</interviewee>
<interviewer>But nowadays in Japan for example they have those robot-free zones where you can basically take your robot and send it out and use it in public without a lot of limitations so is that view changing in terms of a lot of safety security?</interviewer>
<interviewee>No still our country in some sense is maybe I should not say that . It's very conservative in some sense in a good word, very conservative. Without regulation we couldn't do anything different. So it's a kind of a contradiction. We'd like to develop something different, get something new. But if it was new we couldn't do any experiments using that system in the public. And of course in these ways they have a kind of special rule. If local authority approves it then we can do some experiments but experiments are very limited. I think that is one of the reasons why Japanese, we couldn't produce different robots. In some sense it's over restricted. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Where did you get funding for this project?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Which one?</interviewee>
<interviewer>The augmented.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Augmentation? Actually we had no funding at the time because we had manipulators . At this time I was young so we don't have so much research fund and so the only two robots is a very precious system for me and we tried to utilize the robot for any purposes to prove that our system works, our control system works very well. At the time  I stick to the design of the new control system which is robust against kind of this disturbance and everything. Originally I was a control guy. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Over the course of your career what have been your primary sources of funding and support for your research? </interviewer>
<interviewee>Actually we have two fundings, three fundings, but in my case of course we have NSF research fund. It's J.S.P.S. [ph?] Researching Aid, _____________ it's called. And another one is N.A.D.O. [ph?], NADO Project and it's funding for the collaborated research with industries. And third one is purely from industries. At this moment I have many research funding. I have several research funding associates [ph?] from industries and the amount is larger than that of the government research fund. And so okay there is a reason why I started a more industrial project is that without being involved in the real issues we don't know what kind of issues exist in the real field. And I notice that many people are trying to do some basic research, fundamental research of robotics, but it's not easy to find that new issues relating to the in the field of robots. But in case of the United States you have a very good system Darpa works very well. You have a lot of interesting initiatives like Grand Challenge and a lot of funding is given for the kind of more the other _____ oriented robotics issues. So in this country researchers I think have some idea concerned with what kind of robotics technology has to be developed for doing for developing new field. But in Japan unfortunately as long as if you said that this research is relating to the kind of application oriented [ph?] and then we couldn't get research fund from J.S.P.S. as well as J.S.T. [ph?] and something. They believe that scientific research only scientific research is fundamental research and which could be applied to many fields which should be applied to many fields and they fund only such research and so they don't know. Usually it's not easy to notice [ph?] kind of a real issues existing in real applications. So now I put more emphasis on kind of a collaborative research between industries because they usually bring us a kind of real issues which contains a lot of interesting scientific issues maybe based on through the collaborative research we could establish some new field. That is what I am trying to do at this moment. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Have you found it difficult to kind of use that also in the scientific community, the kinds of results that are more application oriented? </interviewer>
<interviewee>Recently-- when this will be published? I'd like to know because depending on when this interview is opened sometimes I couldn't say something. </interviewee>
<interviewer>It will be at least a year. It will be yeah, not this year. More than a year. </interviewer>
<interviewee>More than a year? Okay. I think for example suppose we are doing some work okay? And then we use both vision [ph?] and haptic [ph?] information okay? And I think we found a very good research topic concerned with kind of the fusion of haptic information as well as visual information. And we are now developing a new controller based on different types of information. So I couldn't say so much at this moment, but I think it's very interesting. The issue came from the industries or through the discussions concerned with some problems which we'd like to solve. We found that we have to develop something different. And I think probably we can develop probably we are going to present it maybe next year.  I hope. </interviewee>
<interviewer>And is this also for a manipulator?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, it's concerned with the manipulator. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Sensor fusion. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes, sensor fusion.   Sensor fusion in some sense. </interviewee>
<interviewer>And who have been some of the corporations, industries that have sponsored your work?</interviewer>
<interviewee>It's secret, confidential. I'm not allowed to say. </interviewee>
<interviewer>But for your whole career? Have there been others that are not secret?</interviewer>
<interviewee>They don't want to admit it, unfortunately. Very interesting. Of course, if the research was open okay then company people do not want to bring me the real issue. It's all-- that's very difficult. Companies in Japan has a different culture. I think I don't know whether it's good or not but they have a different culture. So based on the kind of contract, more strict contract we can see the real issues. And what we can do is try to I want to say abstract the issue and so that we can utilize the results to many different fields. </interviewee>
<interviewer>And then you can publish it basically when it's not related exactly to…</interviewer>
<interviewee>That's right.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Do you think there's a difference in the patent structures in Japan from the U.S. and Europe that make that…</interviewer>
<interviewee>Patent structure may be the same, I think so. Yes, the same. But the one difference is-- I don't know whether I can say but this is true.  So keep this part secret, in some sense. It's very strange. Okay. Japanese companies they try to get all of the patents which will be produced through the collaborative research. It's not so good. Okay. If our university holds the patents, we can use the patents for different applications. But usually, people say that the company people are trying to keep the patents by themselves. So we are encouraged to sell the rights of the patents to the companies. Actually, we developed several plug to go systems. We've got patents. And unfortunately our university has sold the patent company so I'm a little bit shocked.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>So you mentioned in '89 and '90 that you went to MIT for a year. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes. </interviewee>
<interviewer>How did you decided to go there?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Because that is-- just after Harry Osada [ph?] went back to the U.S. and when he was staying at the Kyoto University he asked me whether I can join his group or not. And at that time, it as a secret that he was going back. And yes I got the invitation in one sense. And he's supported my living expenses in Boston. And that's why I joined his group. Again, the data was very interesting. MIT is an exciting place. And yes I learned a lot again. And during-- it was only one year but I really learned a lot. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Who were the people who were there? And the kinds of projects that were happening at the time at MIT?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, I don't remember. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Who did you work with basically?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay.  I was working with the-- Harry [ph?] has his own idea concerned with the robot structure. So we've got-- by each rising the drive motor we developed-- I don't know the name of the student, but I think probably Kevin. So this part should not be included.  He may be disappointed that I forgot their names. By using the drive motors which I received from a company another student developed a planer link manipulator system. So my work was, at the time, is how to implement the-- I built the control system which could-- kind of a master service control system but using that data to drive motor. And, of course, I was interested in the how to make it the--- how to create different type of intelligent control system but one year was too short for me. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Who were some other people that you've collaborated with over the years?</interviewer>
<interviewee>At MIT over the years?</interviewee>
<interviewer>Everywhere, Japan and the world. </interviewer>
<interviewee>So it's a difficult question. In some sense I'm doing everything by myself. . I was doing everything by myself in the past. And so until recently I think in some sense my research is self-contained. And recently I noticed that the collaboration is very important and I tried to invite several professors in our university. And we are doing something different by converging different technologies. I'm good at the control part of the manipulator, forced control or impedance control. It's my favorite area. And some guy from vision join that. And some guy from mechanical design part joined us. And, again, robotics is a kind of product based on the technology convergence. And I like the collaboration with other people. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Can you say who the vision and mechanical person were?</interviewer>
<interviewee>I don't know. </interviewee>
<interviewer>You're like James Bond. </interviewer>
<interviewee>No, no. I'm not sure, whether I can.  Yeah. Because that's related to the kind of confidential projects. At this moment I should not say that. </interviewee>
<interviewer>We'll know in a year. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah, hopefully. Yes. </interviewee>
<interviewer>So how did you start working on the dancer project?  Because you talked a lot about these realistic applications and things like that. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay. At the time, when I started the dancer project we are doing some cooperative robot control system, cooperative control of multiple mobile robots handling a single object in coordination. And at the time I was interested in how to make the robot more intelligent. Of course, the definition of intelligence is not so easy.  So I thought that maybe it might be a good idea to develop kind of a pet robot. So I wanted to develop a mobile pet robot. We named it Moped [ph?]. But unfortunately the student who was involved in the Moped project-- in my lab, each student has his or her own kind of research topic. He's been hospitalized for two months or something. So we noticed that we didn't have enough time for him to do something in the Moped because that is a completely different field from our previous experiences. And so we had a discussion and I noticed that maybe if we created something different, probably I mean that could be appreciated-- that could be utilized as a master of thesis, at the time of the student, a master course student. And also through the multiple robot coordination-- we are doing a lot of things. Multiple robot coordination and human/robot coordination. And especially the human/robot coordination through the several experiments over a human/robot coordination it turned out that we needed something different for the robots. Of course, in these days, many people are interested in how to develop a robot assistant, for example. In order to assist a human, for a robot, the robot has to know what the human is doing, what its user is doing, how its user would like to be assisted. Or what kind of a task the guy is doing. And all over the-- such information is very important. How, he or she is trying to do, in some sense their intentions. Without this information and the robot couldn't assist the human. Up to the collaborate, I want to say the physical at that time we have a very limited knowledge concern with the human/robot interaction. That's from based on the pure control system design. So we found that something is missing. So we thought it's a good idea to develop a ballroom dance robot. And in case of ballroom dance the male dancer leads the female dancer. So if we could develop a female dancer, we could reproduce the female dancer as a function then probably we could apply the results for the assistant robot for future robots which could assist humans. So this idea combined with the situation of that student and in some sense created the idea of a dance partner robot by utilizing mobile robot.  We have several mobile robots. And we decided to use one of the robots. We modify the mobile robot so that it could dance with a human and that is really the starting point. I think it's around 1997. And, of course, after that we had are doing-- the new students continue the research and fortunately in 2005, IJ Expo provided help in Japan. We gave a proposal for the NATO [ph?] project and saying that I would like to demonstrate a dance partner robot. And our proposal was accepted. And so we could hire the designer. It turned very interesting. A designer of the well-known dance partner robot PBDR is Tatsio Kanogi [ph?] who is a real designer, dress designer. And when we found him, we met him, he was one of the key designers of Issey Miyake's group. Issey Miyake is a well-known designer in Japan. And after that he left the group and he's now independent. And so we had a collaboration with the designer, dress designer. And also in order to have a demonstration of our robot during IJ Expo-- actually it was a two week demonstration. It's not so long but it's not a one-time demonstration. So we thought that it was not easy to give everything by ourselves. So we found a company, a generous company to support us to develop the robot. And so the company and it's called Nomali Nissan. Now, they changed the name. It's called Nomali Nissan and Mr. Okonogi [ph?] and ourselves set up a group. And Mr. Okonogi has a lot of his own networks. He found a good mannequin company who could produce beautiful outer panel of the robot. And himself a design created a completely different design of a dancer partner robot. And it's really beautiful. And when I saw the first, what I say, we saw the mannequin company which produced the outer panel is located in Kyoto. We are located in Sendai. And Mr. Okonogi is located in Tokyo. And Nomali Nissan is located in Chino City in Nagano Prefecture. So four different entities are involved in the project. And, again, we learned a lot. And we noticed that we don't know so much about how to produce something different. </interviewee>
<interviewer>How did people react to the dancing robot?</interviewer>
<interviewee>The reaction was so nice. Actually, before that our robot actually a third generation robot was in some sense it was broadcasted. And we had some presentation in the ABSJ [ph?], Robotics Society of Japan's annual conference. And one media is interested in the robot. And they filmed our robot. And several broadcasting companies broadcasted the robot. Then the other time I was all ready in Sendai and one of the companies were Sendai they broadcasted the dance partner robot and the original version and newscaster said that she doesn't like her face, the face of the robot. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Was it at that point the turquoise and the pink one?</interviewer>
<interviewee>No, a different design, original one. Actually, that's the third generation. So in some sense we are disappointed to hear the comments and in some sense discouraged. So this ITX plus project was really nice by inviting the real designer, dress designer. Of course, he's a major designer of dress, he has his own idea, how to make the system, the robot is more attractive to the ordinary people.  It's very beautiful. And according to him our robot is a kind of combination of a Mickey Mouse and Marilyn Monroe. I don't know how to pronounce it in the precise way and actress, well known actress. And according to him in order to attract-- make the robot attractive to the ordinary people then he said that design should be kind of a combination of well-known characters. He didn't want to make the robot like human. So he include the kind of design, similar to the Mickey Mouse. It has large ears. And Marilyn Monroe is maybe his favorite actress. So by combining them actually it's very beautiful. And also the first part of the demonstration consists of a slow dance. A slow dance was created by my students and together with Mr. Okonogi. And it was, again, very beautiful. So it could attract many people.  After that, actually, of course, we did a demonstration of the physical human/robot interaction. Our student, Dr. Takeda, has danced with the robot. And yeah it was successfully done and many people likes the robot. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Do you think that's your most famous robot?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes. I think still people know. </interviewee>
<interviewer>What about technically?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Technically it's kind of a-- I'm not sure whether I could say that-- behavior estimation, estimation of the next step, following step based on the resultant force applied to the upper body from the male dancer. And we designed in some sense a behavior, a step estimator based on the--  by utilizing _______ model and it works. Of course, we are still doing the research, how to increase the robustness or how to make the system more adaptable, adaptive to the different people. Yeah, we found a lot of issues. And actually, during the CIPRA [ph?] conference, one student, our student, Mr. Honogone [ph?] is going to give a presentation concerned with how to realize couple the dynamics of both dancers. It's another issue. </interviewee>
<interviewer>What do you think is the biggest technical challenge to this kind of human/robot physical interaction?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Of this interaction? Of course, the different types of-- physical human/robot interaction means a lot of different things. So probably they-- okay, generally speaking most of the difficult issue is how to create safety, safetyness [ph?]. The robot has to be safe. So it's kind of issues which we have to solve. But in our case, in case of dance robot several issues, one is how to estimate the human's behavior. This is also general.  Suppose that we try to develop an assistant robot, the robot has to know the human's intention, in some sense intention estimation or behavior estimation, more precisely. And the next one is in our case, in the case of dance robot it issues kind of a synchronization of motions or a couple dynamics. So suppose that you would like to do something together with the robot, suppose that you like to carry something like a desk, together with a robot. These two dynamics have to be in some sense have to be coordinated. And sometimes you may need some synchronization. Okay. And another one is-- I'm sorry, I'm not very organized.  And another one is as long as robot is interact with the human-- the human may expect some characters, some emotions in the robot. So emotional behavior, emotional aspects should be implemented in the robot system. That's kind of our final goal. It's really difficult. We are starting with the physical human/robot interaction means that kind design and control first and then try to move it to the in some sense intelligent part. So we are still trying to climb up the stairs, climb up the mountain and that takes time. </interviewee>
<interviewer>And is this also funded by industry? Or is this funded by the government?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Which one?</interviewee>
<interviewer>The dancer. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Now, of course, concerning dance robot in the past we received research fund from JSPS and also NATO [ph?], the IJ Expo [ph?] and the country that we are doing that by ourselves. </interviewee>
<interviewer>What do you consider the biggest technical accomplishments of your career?  </interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay.  It might not be theoretical. I'd like to say based on this human/robot interaction experiments with dance robots we found several applications in the industries. One is PaDY and it's a robot which is supposed to be utilized for the automobile companies, factories. And at least in Japan there is a lot of workers, human workers still involved in assembling of automobiles. And sometimes they have to go back to the workbench to pick up parts and put the parts to the vehicle. And we found that by developing kind of an assistant robot which assisted these workers to assemble the parts, maybe the workers we can make their work more efficient. So our robot is parts and the tools delivery robot. PaDY stands for, it's a bit strange English, parts tools delivery to you robot, PaDY. And the robot captures some parts necessary for the assembly. So the worker is doing some assembly task and then the robot is going to bring him or her different parts. So the robot has to estimate to which extent the work has been done, which parts is necessary for him or her to do the next assembly task or something like that. So it depends in some sense, the concept is completely comes from the dance partner robot which we expected at the beginning. But some people may be interested in why we didn't develop a home use robot. Because in some sense now many people are trying to develop robot for home use. But home is a really, really difficult environment. We have an older user which means that the robot have to be completely safe. We couldn't educate the user at home. So in case of factories by limiting the kind of-- first we can educate the user. The user is a worker and usually are educated for that productions system.  And we can control the environment. Of course, it's in some sense it's less unstructured than compared to the home. So I think it might be a good idea to bring the robot assistant into the factory first. Then based on the several experiences in the factories, probably that concept could be brought into the real ordinary environment.  I think we are still working on it. And it's exciting, very exciting. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Did it help you improve your dancing?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Pardon?</interviewee>
<interviewer>Did it help you improve your dancing, the dance robot?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah. Yeah. </interviewee>
<interviewer>The student did all of the dancing.  </interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, unfortunately I couldn't dance. </interviewee>
<interviewer>So who are some of your more successful students who are still working in robotics?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Still working on robotics and successful students?  In our case, since maybe since we are doing a lot of system integration type of research and so many people after having got a Ph.D. and many people would like to join the companies.  And many students are working in companies. Some of them are developing next generation robots and some of them are doing something different. And concerned with the academia, yes and my associate professor is old student. This is Professor Hirata [ph?]. And he's trying to apply the kind of physical human/robot interaction technology to the assistive systems, I mean assistive systems of the walking assisted system or other types, usually mainly mobility assistive system for the elderly or some disabled person. I think he's most successful. </interviewee>
<interviewer>Can you also tell us a little bit about your work for RAS and RSJ?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah, and the JSME.  Somehow I have been heavily involved in society activities. In Japan I was kind of-- there are three societies relating to the robots. One is SICE, Society of Instrument and Control Engineers. When I was member of the board of directors, board of governors, we established a new division in that society, the Society of Instrument and Control Engineers. That division is system integration division. Okay. I was kind of the head of the division and also served as kind of several positions in the board of governors in that organization.  And after that I was also concerned with the Robotics Society of Japan. Again, I was a…</interviewee>
</interview>
</subject>
