<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<subject>
<name>Ken Waldron</name>
<interview>
<interviewer>Okay.  So if we could start by having you say your name and where you were born.</interviewer>
<interviewee>My name is Ken Waldron.  I was born in Sydney, Australia and most of my education was at the University of Sydney.  I have a bachelor of engineering degree and a master of engineering science from there and I got my Ph.D. here at Stanford with Bernie Roth and I subsequently did receive a doctor of engineering degree from the University of Sydney in 1999.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So how did you get interested in engineering to begin with?</interviewer>
<interviewee>I've often wondered about that.  It seemed like a good idea at the time, I guess.  I had a grandfather who worked as a draftsman at the Water Board in Sydney and he kind of fed me stuff when I was a teenager which I guess got me interested and then I got a traineeship from the Australian Steel Industry, which meant that I went to work for them on vacations and I got some salary and stuff like that so that seemed like a very good idea at the time.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What made you decide to come to the States to continue your education?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, when I came to consider doing a doctoral degree, most advanced students in Australia at the time went to England.  I was interested in things that people here in the States were better at than anybody in England and I didn't want to do what everybody else did, anyway, so I wound up coming here.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What were some of the things that the U.S. was better at?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Hm?</interviewee>
<interviewer>What were the things?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, at the time, it was mechanism and machine theory, kinematics and dynamics of mechanisms.  There was hardly anybody in England working in that area at the time so it was much easier to find people here or in Germany or some place like that.</interviewee>
<interviewer>When did you first meet Bernie Roth?</interviewer>
<interviewee>When I came here as a graduate student in 1965, June, 1965.</interviewee>
<interviewer>How did you meet him?</interviewer>
<interviewee>How did I meet him?  I think I had just arrived and I climbed up the big flight of stairs in engineering corner to his office on the top floor and walked in and said, "Here I am."  </interviewee>
<interviewer>Did you know him before you came?</interviewer>
<interviewee>We'd corresponded in...</interviewee>
<interviewee>...the area of research of system ships, yeah.  He knew I was coming.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So you came to be his student?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What were some of the projects that you worked on with Bernie in those early years?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, well, my doctoral thesis was actually a topic I brought with me that I'd been tinkering around with in Australia, which was in the area of mobility of linkages, just counting links and identifying how many degrees of freedom the whole assemblage would have based on its geometry.  But, at the time, the really early work in robotics was going on, too, so I sort of got involved in that by osmosis.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>So what kind of work in robotics did you see or get involved in?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, the last year I was here, Bernie went on sabbatical and I was put on as an acting assistant professor to teach his courses.  At the time, Vic Shineman was designing the Stanford Arm and so I wound up being his advisor of record so I was involved in that project.  Also, I was sharing an office with Don Piper and Mike Kahn at the time when Don was doing one of the first versions of inverse reg kinematics and I happened to know a good deal about the algebraic geometry involved so we talked about that quite a bit.  So, you know, it wasn't my work but I got to contribute some ideas maybe.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Who were some of the other people here who you might have worked with or exchanged ideas with?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, Lou Pole was up in the AI lab at the time and I used the computer up there for my doctoral work so I spent quite a bit of time up there.  Let's see, who else?  Oh, Vic Shineman I've already mentioned.  There was a guy by the name of Spalding who I wound up essentially advising him for the year, too.  I don't know where he wound up.  That's about the lot.  Salisbury was a bit later.  I don't think we overlapped.  Yeah, I think that's about it.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Was there much robotics going on within the AI lab?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, yeah.  Yeah.  There was shaky- not shaky but the old Rancho arm that shivered and shook while it was stacking blocks and stuff like that.  That was really  a lot of the motivation for the Stanford arm.  Then there was the hydraulic arm that Bernie's students put together, which was a fearsome beast and terrified everybody.  I remember one day, the guys who were working on that, and I don't remember their names now, one of the hydraulic valves stripped out its mounting screws and flew off and sprayed everybody with hydraulic oil, which, of course, was a very exciting event.  There was up in that AI lab, which was a wood frame building, and this machine was quite heavy and very fast.  The computer scientists thought computers are fast so it's got to be fast, which was absolutely wrong, actually, but, anyway.  They hadn't got the interface between the mechanical system and the computer right so, every so often, the thing would just take off on its own and swing round.  That lightweight building would kind of jump off its foundations.  So one of the jobs Vic got was to cut a hole in the floor and pour a great big block of concrete to bolt this thing down to and they put an enclosure around it so nobody could get in there.  But then they thought, well, most of the time, it just sits there waiting for the computer to make its mind up so why don't we build something that's a bit more user friendly.  That's what turned into the Stanford arm project.  Are you talking to Vic, by the way?</interviewee>
<interviewer>We talked to Vic.</interviewer>
<interviewee>All right.  So you've got all the story on that.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What were some of the discussions at the time here about robotics and some of the possibilities that you can remember?</interviewer>
<interviewee>I think, at the time, we were kind of preoccupied with sort of the basic of computer controlled manipulation, how to get the machine to the position you wanted in some kind of reasonably controlled manner and how to perform basic manipulation tasks, you know?  Things that, these ays, people hardly think twice about them.  Back then, it was a big deal.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Why the choice of manipulation?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Hm?</interviewee>
<interviewer>Why the choice of manipulation?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, the industry seemed to want that, okay?  You know, this was the same period of time when Engelberger was building the first Unimate or had recently built it.  That was doing simple industrial tasks like removing molds from die casting machines and stuff like that.  Basically, it was just an arm that did simple tasks.  Well, that's manipulation so that was the initial focus.  As you, I'm sure, know, Vic went on to design the Puma and some other kinds of manipulators in industry.  So, at the time, that was the focus.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What kind of mechanisms were you, yourself, interested in?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, back then, I was, you know, I suppose I did some theory on these manipulation tasks.  Somewhat later, I went to Ohio State University and hooked up with Bob McGee and we started- he had already been doing leg machines and I got involved in that.  That machine on the wall behind you was one of the things we did.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So how did you end up in Ohio State?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, well, that's a long story.  After I graduated from here, I went back to Australia.  I was in a faculty position at the University of New South Wales.  My wife was, also.  She is not Australian, she is Indian.  I think she was a little uncomfortable there.  We also have a child, our eldest child is deaf and he needed some special education opportunities.  So we made the decision to come back to the States.  In the meantime, we'd done a sabbatical, part of which was spent at the University of Maryland.  While there, I went and visited one of my old roommates from here at the University of Houston and discovered I was being interviewed.  So I wound up accepting a faculty position at the University of Houston.  After five years there, that wasn't working so well.  Looked around some and what was available was Ohio State so that's where I went.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What was the kind of work that you did at Houston?</interviewer>
<interviewee>I didn't do any robotics there, I don't think.  I did mechanism theory work there.  That was one of the frustrations there, there wasn't the opportunity.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So when you came to Ohio State, Bob McGee was already working in robotics?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes.  He'd been doing that while he was working on leg locomotion.  He'd been doing that since the late '60s so that was about ten years before I got there.</interviewee>
<interviewer>How did you get involved with Bob McGee?</interviewer>
<interviewee>I already knew him because I'd met him at robotics conferences overseas, actually.  I thought the stuff that he was doing was interesting so, when I got there, I made a point of going to meet him and one thing led to another from there.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What was the first project you worked on together?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, I worked some on the old OSU Hexapod.  I don't think I was ever formally a part of that project but, you know, tried to contribute-- well, I remember working out, for example, the final inertia ratio on the thing which had Black and Decker drill motors and a pretty large ratio gear box between the motor and the joint.  So the reflected inertia was huge and I then did an estimate of how much energy the thing was wasting just coming to a halt and reversing direction every step.  It was about six kilowatts or something.  It was pretty impressive.  And then, when DARPA came to talk to him about doing the big machine, which turned into that thing up there, and he needed somebody to look after the mechanical design, it was an easy step to put together a team.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So what was the DARPA project?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Basically the fundamental idea was to build a vehicle for transportation in very rough terrain and, because of the limitations of wheels and tracks in those circumstances, they were interested in looking at a legged solution.  And we were interested in that so that's what we did.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What year was this?</interviewer>
<interviewee>That project started in 1981 and it finished up in, I think, 1990.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What were some of the interesting questions for you?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, we worked, I think I could say, we reworked all the theory of statically stable locomotion.  One of my students, Simon Song, and myself, particularly, did that.  This book was basically Simon's doctoral dissertation with an additional chapter added that I wrote myself to provide a general description of the machine.  I better get that out; otherwise, it will disappear forever.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So what was the next big robotics project that you took up?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, after that finished, I'm having a hard time remembering.  I did some smaller projects.  I did come here on sabbatical and was involved with Bernie and Ursula Katib [ph?] in what he called the Artisan Project, which was a redundant robot that had both series and parallel elements and, in fact, I did a design for a parallel wrist for that robot.  And Bernie and I and Monty Regevan [ph?] wrote a couple of papers on the kinematics of mixed serial parallel robot configurations, which I think were fairly influential.  And so that actually came into the same timeframe as the ASV work.  And sometime, it wasn't all that long after that, that-- well, I continued to do mobile robot work, not only legs but also wheels and tracks.  I had become involved in that and produced several student dissertations out of all that.  And then I became department chairman and my research kind of slid for awhile.  After that, I came here and did some more mobile robot work on joint DARPA and SAR I/C sponsorship.  Did some more leg robot work, part of it was a project that I'd brought from Ohio State on a dynamically stable quadruped, which is still over in my lab there.  And subsequently I also did some dynamically stable biped work.  Those are the major things that I've been involved in.</interviewee>
<interviewer>How did you get back to Stanford?</interviewer>
<interviewee>I had a lot of friends here and I kind of asked Bernie if he could fix up a-- basically, a soft bunny position.  I'm called, well, I was until I retired, called a professor brackets research here, which was similar to what we called a senior research scientist at Ohio State.  Well, as department chairman at Ohio State, I could have fixed a position like that in two weeks.  It took 18 months here  but it happened in the end.  And I decided that that's what I wanted to do so I came out.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Were there other people while you were at Ohio State that you worked with?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes.  David Aran I worked with.  Chuck Cline I worked with there.  Gary Kinsel [ph?] in my own department and Neger Bermais [ph?] also in my own department.  I think- oh, and then there were a couple of people in computer science we worked with occasionally, Bruce Whitey, who's the most active of those.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What are some of the major contributions that you feel you've made through?</interviewer>
<interviewee>That takes some thought.  Well, you know, obviously, the whole thing of statically stable walking machines, I did a lot of stuff on that.  Earlier on, I did some work which kind of followed on from my doctoral work here on synthesis of planar mechanisms, which had nothing to do with robotics but I think was fairly important.  Less important, but it still impresses people, there's several versions of the Hartenberg and Denavit notation that are used but the one that is most used was the one that I used in my doctoral dissertation.  Again, it was before anything to do with robotics.  I think, in terms of understanding the mechanics of dynamic quadrupedal locomotion, I think we're ahead of anybody else, including Marc Raibert.  He has had great success in the walking and trotting gaits, which are symmetric and less baffling than a gallop.  We have focused on galloping and we still I would say don't have a complete understanding but I think we know more about it than anybody else.  Still writing papers on that.  And I'm sure there was a bunch of other things in between but-- well, did do some of the early work in parallel robotic architectures and I know that's still cited fairly frequently.  And with Vijay Kumar, who was my student at the time at Ohio State, we did some very basic work on the coordination of multi-limbed systems which was very widely cited.  Of course, he's had a very successful career of his own.</interviewee>
<interviewer>How would you categorize some of the approaches that you've used to mobility?</interviewer>
<interviewee>I beg your pardon?</interviewee>
<interviewer>How would you categorize some of the approaches that you used over the years?  So are you inspired more kind of mathematically or by actual biological mechanisms, a combination?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, I think, you know, my sort of roots go back to kinematic theory.  That's what I first learned about in Australia and which I continued to study when I was here as a doctoral student.  But I subsequently became involved in hardware design and I think I was successful at that and what is now called mechatronics.  Did a lot of that with the ASV, a lot of it with other systems, even going back to the days of the Stanford arm long before it was called mechatronics.</interviewee>
<interviewer>How would you say mechatronics relates to robotics?</interviewer>
<interviewee>I regard robotics as a subset of mechatronics.  Mechatronics is integrating computers with mechanical systems of whatever description.  A robot, of course, is such a system but there are other systems that we probably wouldn't call robots which are certainly mechatronics systems like that thing there.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So are there also, through your work, have you considered your work specifically on particular applications of mechanisms that you've designed?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, I have to say that, you know, my orientation has always been basic science. So I haven't-- well, you know, I have gotten involved in some applications. But I would say that was fairly peripheral to what I do. I have used biomimetic inspiration, of course, at various times, certainly, with the locomotion work. But, you know, you use that to provide inspiration. You don't try to copy nature because we're not good enough to do that.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And what are some of the organisms that you might have been inspired by for different projects?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, when we were doing the ASV, we had a collaborator who took high speed photographs of grasshoppers crawling over obstacles and stuff like that. So we studied that a lot. Then we had another collaborator who did experiments with goats, figuring out how they managed their legs and how they dealt with obstacles and how they-- those were the main things. And so, we-- and then more recently, of course, Mark Kokovski [ph?] works with Bob Full [ph?] up at Berkeley and uses a whole variety of animals from cockroaches to geckos to whatever. And, you know, we interacted a little on that, so a whole variety of beasties at various times.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Who are some other people that you've collaborated with over the years ?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Former students or international? Well, I was the president of IFToMM for eight years. IFToMM is the International Federation for Promotion of Mechanist and Machine Science. And, you know, I have a whole bunch of people overseas that I've interacted with fairly intensively, people like Jorge Angeles who's maybe on your list of interviewees even though he's in Canada not the U.S. And people like Adam Morecki, who is no longer with us, John Vetou [ph?], who much earlier passed away, who was a very innovative person in the robotics area, did some very important work in France and Giovanni Bianchi in Italy, and several of Morecki's students, including Teresa Syolenska [ph?] and a bunch of people in France, Phillipe Nadeau [ph?], Jean-Pierre Merlan [ph?]. And some of my buddies in Australia are Jim Trevelyan is one, Hugh Durrant-Whyte and Gamini Dissanayake. And he's still a colleague. I spend time each year at the University of Technology in Sydney with him. So it's a whole variety of people.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And who are some of the students of yours who have gone on to work in robotics?</interviewer>
<interviewee>I mentioned Vijay Kumar who of course has been extremely successful. Svay Swenovasim [ph?] at the University of Texas has been enormously successful in building things like machines to replicate integrated circuits and stuff like that. So I guess he's not really doing robotics per se anymore. Who else? Samuel Aguele [ph?] who was with me for a Master's degree and then switched to ___________ for his doctorate. He's been highly successful. And there's others, a number who have been very successful in the industry. And-- yeah, I'm sure if I went down the list, I could find some more.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Have you done any work with industries?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, I've done dozens of industry sponsored projects, yes. I still got a little sponsorship from General Motors, for example, which, again, is not robotics. It's hybrid drive trains basically, the mechatronics fundamentally.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Could you talk a little bit about some of those and what kinds of things the industry has been interested in over the years?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah. Well, some of the industry work was the stuff I did with SAIC, which was basically mobile robots mostly not legged, mostly, you know, wheels and tracks. Then earlier than that, I worked with Martin Marietta Aerospace, as they called themselves at the time, in Denver. And we built a legged robot there, which was a-- for the potential Mars Rover Project before NASA changed direction and changed direction again. But back in the days when they were thinking of a fairly ambitious Rover project-- the large sized rover, we proposed a huge six or seven legged machine for that. And I did most of the mechanical design of that. They actually built a core to scale prototype and drove it around the __________ box up there. And let's see, I've done some actuation work for industry. That was General Motors again. And that was polymer actuators, again a mechtronics project not a robotics project.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And what other places have you received funding from? You mentioned DARPA?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Most of my funding has actually been NSF. I got more or less continuous funding from them for many years.  And I've also-- I haven't mentioned any of the Australian stuff. I got some funding from the Australian Research Council there with a colleague at UTS to build a robot to do inspection on steel bridges. And we still argue over whether that's a legged machine or a wheeled machine or what geometry it is. But, you know, basically climbing around truss work, it'll have legs of some sort. And it will have some adhesion mechanism whether it's electromagnets or something, permanent magnets or something else. Again, it's something we're still arguing over.</interviewee>
<interviewer>You mentioned that you did a second PhD in Australia. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, now it wasn't a second PhD. It was a doctor of engineering degree, which is one where you submit a compilation of your published work as a thesis. And it's examined by a bunch of people around the world. And that is kind of my ultimate degree.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And you've been to obviously Stanford multiple times, so how has it changed do you think over the years, the kinds of directions people are taking there?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, back when I was here as a student, you know, the design division was very new and unstable, shall we say. A lot of the early faculty that either didn't get tenure or didn't stay for other reasons and Bernie was one of those young junior professors at that time who did stick. And  as I say, back then, sort of robotics was a very new thing. The AI Lab did exist. And we've talked a bit about that. And I know you've talked to John McCarthy and he was directing that at the time. There was a whole sort of bunch of semi temporary buildings over there. My wife had an office in one of those. She was a PhD student in electrical engineering. And all of that's been bulldozed and replaced by the flashy new buildings and things like that. So the campus has changed a lot. The design division has gone from being new and unstable to being very well established in a central part of the chemical engineering department here. So that's different.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What was Bernie Roth like to work with as a student?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, I enjoyed working with him. At the time, he was a lousy lecturer. He's since become an excellent lecturer but at the time he wasn't. But he was-- I enjoyed working with him. And I have to give him credit. You know, he let me do basically a project that I brought with me from Australia on his funding. So that was kind of a unique situation. And actually, it was quite a long time after I finished and went my own way that we finally published a paper together. He is not an author on any of my early papers. Yeah, we're still good friends.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And what were some of the challenges of working on mechanical design that happened over the years? And how have they changed __________ from, you know, the accumulation of knowledge or from, you know, technological capabilities that perhaps were lacking?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, the whole set of technologies is usually called rapid prototyping happened relatively recently. And that makes an enormous difference. You know, a student can now sit down at a computer and do a solid model and put the model to a laser cam or something and build parts in a very short period of time. So it's so much easier to build prototype hardware. So we can think about, you know, building lots of prototypes to try out ideas and things, which you simply didn't do back when building a prototype was enormously expensive and required lots of time. So all of that's different. And it has-- you know, you have to change the way you think because sort of back when I was a student, you wouldn't think of building anything unless you had a really big grant to pay for all the costs. And now, you kind of don't do anything without thinking of building hardware.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What were some of the challenges of like the parallel risks? You described sort of the hybrids systems.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, at the time, nobody had really thought about the kinematic equations for those things and how you would control them because, you see the way you-- the mathematics works for parallel systems is fundamentally different from the way the mathematics works for a serial system. And what's easy in a serial system is difficult in a parallel system and vice versa. So putting them together in trying to run a system that had both features at the time was something that nobody had explored. So we had to roll up our sleeves and I think do some pretty fundamental stuff to just work out how you would indeed do that.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What do you think are some of the outstanding challenges or things that people are still kind of-- questions that are important to ask in the next, I don't know, five, 10 years?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, where to start? There's so many of them really. You know, the one that always frustrates me is actuation. And I've done quite a few projects myself trying to improve that. But, you know, fundamentally, things like electric motors are rotten. If you compare them to what we can do, you know, biologically, they're pathetic. And yeah, hydraulic actuators are much stronger and very quick and all that. But they have a whole bunch of problems themselves including being very wasteful of energy. And when you think about it, a muscle fiber converts chemical to mechanical energy in a micro mechanical package. And we can't even remotely approach that. Our usual way of converting chemical to mechanical energy after all is a heat engine. And so, there's enormous scope for things that we can't yet do. The whole thing of human interactive robotics, which I know is a very hot area right now. But yeah, we're not very good at that. That's some very fine stuff over there. Essentially, making the mechanical system so the different-- it whaps you. It won't kill you. It'll hurt  but, you know, maybe you don't have to fence the robot off. But really, the-- what's missing is the massive paralleled sensing that we have and the ability to process all that information. If you have that, you probably wouldn't need to make the-- you know, the robot soft. It would be smart enough not to do things that would damage people. But we're light years away from that life. And I know there's going to be a lot of government funding and a lot of research effort going to that. And we'll see what happens. But I think we've got a long, long way to go.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What are some of the big breakthroughs that you've witnessed over the years?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, the first and biggest was simply the integration of computers with mechanical systems, which changed the landscape enormously. And before that, you thought in terms of building a machine with a single big motor, turning it and coordinating everything mechanically. And nowadays, the game is you individually actuate joints and coordinate them in software. That's a totally different way of doing things. So that was important. I've already mentioned the rapid prototyping development and of course computer aided design or computer aided engineering of all sorts. It all happened during my career. So that was a vast change also. Back when I was doing my doctorate, you know, you did a lot of graphical computation. That was very rapidly taken over by computer aided design type software. And it was, in fact, a very interesting problem, learning to use that because the best ways to do things in the computer are not the same as the best ways to do them with a pencil and paper.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Did you ever run into Regina [ph?] ____________ when you were here?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh yeah, I knew Regina quite well. Not here. I knew her at UPENN and of course, subsequently at Berkeley.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Did you ever collaborate on anything with her?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Not really. We did talk a lot for a while on-- and of course she hired Vijay. And yeah, there was a vivid of conversation but I don't think any formal collaboration.</interviewee>
<interviewer>What was the conversation about?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, of course, she is more of a perception person. I'm a mechanical systems guy. And she was, at the time, interested in bolstering the ability of her lab to do mechanical things. And Vijay was one person who early on helped with that. Lou Pole [ph?], of course, was there at the time but he had gone to the dean's office and is no doubt busy with other things. Zho Ping [ph?], who's now at the Naval post graduate at the School at Monterey, was there early on and working with her. So, you know, I knew all those people and talked to them. But that's about as far as it went.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Okay and if you had some advice for young people who might be interested in robotics, particularly, perhaps in the design, what would it be?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, I think, you know, robotics has always been kind of a difficult animal to deal with because it does involve so many different technologies in an integrated way. What I advise my own students to do here is to take all the mechatronics courses they can get hold of, and there is a good series here, and then to do the, you know, basic robotics course sequence to get the fundamental mathematics and stuff. And there's also-- we have good computer vision courses, which I advise them to do. But, you know, the world's changing. I'm not sure I can tell them what to expect beyond a year or two after they graduate.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And what was Vijay like as a student?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, Vijay. was wonderful. You know, I didn't work with him like a student. I worked with him like a colleague. And, you know, I suppose I put the problems before him. But he'd go away and come back with a solution kind of thing, you know. He was fun.</interviewee>
<interviewer>And are there any other stories you'd like to share?</interviewer>
<interviewee>There have been other very good students too. Jim Schmiedeler who's now at Notre Dame, was another student like that who was great fun to work with. More recently, Alex Perkins who is now at Boston Dynamics and Paul Csonka who's about to graduate, have all been very fun people to work with.</interviewee>
<interviewer>This is all we have unless you have something you would like to add.</interviewer>
<interviewee>No, I think I'm about bled dry.</interviewee>
<interviewer>I hope you'll revive very quickly . Thank you. Thank you very much.</interviewer>
<interviewee>So this will be in the</interviewee>
</interview>
</subject>
