<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<subject>
<name>Vijay Kumar</name>
<interview>
<interviewee>You want me to just go down this list or are you going to ask these questions?</interviewee>
<interviewer>I can ask you questions. </interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay.</interviewee>
<interviewer>So if we could first start with where you were born and some of your early educational experience that would be great.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay.  Should I look at you or look at the camera?</interviewee>
<interviewer>You can look at either one of us.  You don't have to look at the camera, whatever you're comfortable with.</interviewer>
<interviewee>You guys are easy.  Sorry. </interviewee>
<interviewer>So where were you born and your early education.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Okay.  So I was born in India in a town called Patna which is in Eastern India.  And I spent most of my life in Central India and then in New Delhi and I went to school in Central India and then in New Delhi and then I</interviewee>
<interviewer>The question that we usually finish with is could you give some advice to young people who are interested in robotics?</interviewer>
<interviewee>How young are these people that you are</interviewee>
<interviewer>It can be any age that you think.  Of course now it's from "K to whatever."</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well okay.  So here's my-- so from the standpoint of education, I think I often call robotics the knautical [sp?] engineering discipline.  And the reason is it's a) it's synthetic.  Unlike many engineering disciplines where you analyze things, here the whole goal of robotics is to build things.  And it forces you to learn the signs that you need to build these things.  So if I was to restructure engineering programs, I would simply have the very first course be a robotics course and from that build engineering science courses that could help students build better robots.  So this is sort of a top-down way of doing robotics.  But getting off that soapbox, I would tell students that this is a good way to learn a wide variety of techniques that are used in engineering.  Well today, robotics doesn't include biology as much as it could so bioengineering and biomedical engineering is not really a central part of robotics but that's just a question of time.  I mean that will also creep in.  Likewise, it may not include chemical engineering or material signs, but I think again it's a question of time.  We're going to be looking for novel materials and so it's really the best way to learn about engineering.  So if you're interested in creating anything in an engineering-type setting, building physical devices, robotics is the discipline to get interested in.  I would also say it really has a truly transformational ability here or potential here.  So if you look at-- so the U.S. is not yet doing this but if you look at, for example, Japan, Korea, Europe, many countries in Europe, in a handful-- if you were to single out a handful of technologies that they're sort of emphasizing, robotics is one of them.  I think we're a little behind the curve, but I would tell people this is where the action is and this is where you need to be.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Why do you think the U.S. is behind the curve?</interviewer>
<interviewee>I think we are a lot more careful about adopting new top-down initiatives.  I think we're a lot more free spirited and I think that's good, that's why I think we attract the best talent.  But if robotics were a social movement then I think everybody would buy into it in a heartbeat.  But I just got off my soapbox but when I was on my soapbox I'm preaching to you and you're not going to accept that, right?  You've got to believe it.  So I think today that kids are believing it.  I mean you see-- we run the first legoly [sp?] competition out of Penn and I was the head of all judges.  So I'm looking at these third graders, these fourth graders, these fifth graders and they're trying to explain to me the basics of control as they see it in the robots and you know that we're connecting with them indirectly.  So I think this is really the discipline to be in that sense and so I think it's a question of time before we buy into it at the level of Washington and below.  And the new robotics 2.0 initiative hopefully will reinforce that.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>Thank you.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Did that help?</interviewee>
<interviewer>Thank you so much.  Yes, no that's great.  </interviewer>
<interviewee>Alright, I'm sorry I didn't</interviewee>
<interviewer>It wasn't so painful right?</interviewer>
<interviewee>No, but I had no idea what I had signed up to.  I thought it was just a bunch of questions.</interviewee>
<interviewer>The other thing would be any people you'd recommend that we interview that may not already be on our list.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well her husband still lives here in Philly.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Okay.  Also, any students you've had who have moved on to be professors.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Oh, I mean I have lots of students.  How much time do we have?  I have to say that's the one part of my job that I really enjoy which is working with doctoral students.  When you-- we work hard at recruiting doctoral students and I just enjoy the process because you try to track the top people and their like uncut stones and all you have to do is home them like until the stones become gems.  And so this is a part that I enjoy a lot.  I've had close to, I think I would say 30 PhD students and a good fraction of them are in academia themselves and several post-docs too, I think close to maybe 20, again many of them are in academia.  And the reason I single out the ones that are in academia-- actually I haven't singled them out, but I mention that is because I think they-- I think I've transmitted my love for sort of supervising of the students to them and I think it's good that they're going on doing the same thing.  So you asked who are-- so just most recently I had-- let's see, the last student to graduate was actually last week, Nurul Amin [sp?]who is-- she is still here.  She is wrapping up her PhD student-- PhD thesis, sorry, and she is looking at academic positions, postdoctoral opportunities.  The one before that, Mahmood Salman Sacar [sp?] is a postdoc at MIT.  And then before that, Spring Berman, she is a postdoc at Harvard.  I can go on and on.  I can give you all kinds of names.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>What about the early ones from the ‘80s?</interviewer>
<interviewee>So my very first PhD student, Nathan Ulrich, was probably the smartest mechanical designer that I ever had, very creative guy.  He ended up doing a postdoc at Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute and then he ended up establishing his own company called Technique.  So he really wanted to create new robots, build new robots and I think he continues to do work on novel devices at this company.  Actually, he and his brother started this company that manufactured high-end scooters.  This is when-- when did scooters become a rage?  Not-- yeah, the push scooters, thank you I was looking for-- so they produced what they called the Rolls Royce of scooters.  So this was people like you and me.  Actually, I have one at home.  So really nice scooters made out of solid stuff, not this "Made in China" kind of production models.  So they made those, they made electric bikes long before electric bikes were a big thing.  Now, of course, you go to Shanghai and any snapshot you take will have seven or ten electric bikes in it.  So he continues to do these kinds of things, creating novel products and bringing them to market.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>Where is that company?</interviewer>
<interviewee>It's based in Boston, actually I don't exactly know where but he is in the Massachusetts area.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Some of your work, has it gone towards particular applications?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Well, I mean when you do research obviously you want to be aware of applications and be guided by them but it's a little dangerous to be obsessed about applications so we try not to do that.  I mean, ultimately, the work that you do even though it's an engineering thesis has to stand on its own, so no we don't particularly think about real applications.  Although, I have to say most recently the project I'm most excited about is one that is really motivated by applications.  So I'm sure you're all aware of the tragedy in Fukushima and it's ironic that the tragedy happened in Japan, a country which is known for its robotics work and yet there was very little that the experts could do.  And there are many reasons for that.  So one of the things we're really interested in doing is to bring aerial robots and apply them to this setting.  And we also want to think about autonomy.  So one of the difficulties in these kind of settings is you cannot peli-operate [sp?] these robots.  You're not allowed to come close to the actual reactor building because of radiation-- dangers of radiation.  Second, even if you come reasonably close, the communications link is greatly impaired because of electromagnetic radiation.  So what that really means is you want a robot that goes autonomously, gathers data, comes back to you and reports.  Well, it may not come back to you, chances are that robot is lost forever, but it has the data, gives you the data and then it dies.  So we're trying to explore this paradigm in the setting of buildings in the Fukushima area.  We're going to start with Sendai this summer, send our robots to some of these collapsed buildings.  And so here's a project where we want to solve this problem, we want to attack this application area and we think there could be obvious benefits here.  So we're doing that.  But, in general, we try not to do things like this.</interviewee>
<interviewer>Do you work with any Japanese collaborators on that?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yes.  So we've just started this collaboration.  We have a pile of grant from NSF to go visit Tohoku University in Sendai and we're going to perform some preliminary experiments this summer.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>So besides your own work, we talked a little bit in the beginning about the GRASP lab and you've also directed the lab for an extended, so we were wondering if you could tell us a little bit about the development of the lab, what it was like when you got there.  Why don't you mention a bit what it was like when you took over the directorship and how it's developed through the years.  Robotics as a program at Pennsylvania.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Yeah, sure.  I mean I think when Rhishna [sp?] was there, she really had the vision to set up the lab.  She also acquired, some really good space for us and helped nurture the lab during its early years.  But when she left, there was a big leadership vacuum and that was pretty challenging to sort of step in, and as I said, they were mostly computer scientists and I was a lone noncomputer scientist yet running a lab which really was part of the computer science department.  I mean that's not to say that my colleagues made me feel welcomed but still it was a challenge.  I think the one big change during my tenure as the director was to take the lab and to bring in more participation from other departments.  We recruited some top notch electrical engineering professors.  And so right now you look at the lab, whether you look at faculty or students or postdocs, it's roughly one-third mechanical engineering, one-third computer science, one-third electrical engineering.  And really, that reflects the true nature of the discipline.  So I would say that it shifted the overall research, if you looked at the lab, it moved more from the perception centric programs-- research programs that Rhishna [sp?] was more interested in and obviously she was the person in the world in that area to, I think, more broad-based programs which brought in control, coordination, communication, design and I think that was a big shift.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>How did you come to be the director?</interviewer>
<interviewee>I don't know.</interviewee>
<interviewer>how does this happen.</interviewer>
<interviewee>Suddenly-- I think it may well have been that-- I mean I was pretty junior at that time but I was the next most senior person after Rhishna [sp?] and I guess it fell into my lap.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>Do you have any favorite stories from the lab or its development?</interviewer>
<interviewee>You know, the one thing that I remember is that-- so from my really early days I remember that I used to come in on Sundays.  Rhishna [sp?] was there on Sundays and all her students were there on Sunday.  And they would all have their weekly meetings with her on Sunday.  And if she was there they were all there.  It was just amazing and I've never seen this culture elsewhere.  That was the one thing that I could not sustain  mostly because of me, once I had a family and so it's hard to do.  But that didn't happen so that was somewhat funny.  The other thing that was actually-- she had this T-shirt, this sweatshirt which had the word "results" printed on the back and that's how she wanted-- I want results and she would turn her back and walk away to her students, that was funny.  But those  Yeah.  And I still tell my students this so they say, "Well I can take this time off?"  And I said, "I don't care as long as you deliver the results."  And that's what it should be about, right?  </interviewee>
<interviewer>How do you see the strengths and ams [sp?] of the robotics program in relative to some of the other robotics programs at MIT or Carnegie Mellon?</interviewer>
<interviewee>So-- yeah I think there are many outstanding programs.  I would say we're among the top five if not the top three.  I think in terms of size, I think Carnegie Mellon is the big outlier, they're about, I would say, 10 times our size.  But I think in terms of-- I think they have a culture of going after big projects, like Grant Challenge for example, while we probably don't.  I think we pay a lot more-- we're probably a lot more academic in nature.  I think we spend a lot more time thinking about doctoral education, not to say they don't, but I think that's one big difference.  MIT's great.  Much of MIT's program is anchored in the artificial intelligence laboratory.  It's sort of computer science and artificial intelligence.  So I think that's the difference.  I think this is sort of unique in the sense that it is common space that's shared by three different departments.  And to this day, you walk into the lab and you have no idea which space belongs to who and to what department.  You walk into the lab you'll see lots of students and I guarantee you will not be able to identify who's a mechanical engineer, who's an electric engineer, who's a computer scientist and I think that's very unique of Penn.  We're also incredibly collaborative.  I think it's-- I'm really amazed by how students write papers together and often times the advisors don't even know that they're collaborating with other students and that's great.  So I think that culture is part of who we are. </interviewee>
<interviewer>How do you think robotics, just particularly the fields that you've been interested in, have changed through the years and what are some of the future challenges?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Let's see, if you look at cooperative robotics, I think one thing that has happened over the years-- so robotics, like many other sciences I think has been greatly influenced by technological advances.  So I think the biggest technological advance obviously is processing, right?  You know about Morris [sp?] law and all those things.  I remember when I was a doctoral student and when we were implementing code we actually had to worry about the number of adds and multiplies in our code to make sure that we weren't overloading the processor.  Again, to put things in perspective, back then a program with 80 86 Intel Processors, if you don't know what that is you have to go back from a Pentium before that came a 486, 386, 286 and then an 86 so it was that long ago.  And so now you don't have to worry about that.  In some sense I think we're  by the largest but in another sense I think it's allowed us to dream and do things that we would have thought to be completely infeasible back then.  I think the other technological change that has happened is I think if you look at the price to performance ratio of sensors that's fallen dramatically.  So we now have a lot more data than we could have hoped for.  And, again, that has influenced how you think about problems.  I think the third thing that I would say is that in going back we just did not have a critical mass of roboticists [sp?] creating robots.  Now, it's relatively easy.  If I want to make a particular robot with some sort of specification, unique specification, for a particular task it's not a big deal, I can do it.  Or, if I'm too lazy or if I don't want to spend my energy do it, I can go buy it.  That was not the case before, right?  So when you think about the work that we do here-- so for example, one of my most successful students, Nathan Michael who is now a research assistant professor here, he decided that he wanted to build his own robots and he took a combination of off-the-shelf parts and fabricated other parts and he built his own multirobot system.  I mean not to take away from his creativity and his novel designs but this was much harder to do a while back.  So I think these technological changes have influenced the way we think about problems and the problems we think about solving.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>So what are some of the new problems they can now think about solving ?</interviewer>
<interviewee>Right, so for instance now we're thinking about deploying 10s of robots in a building-- in this engineering complex.  So for instance, last year we-- so I told you about Nathan, he was involved in this too.  We did an experiment where we had-- we told the robot to go not just into the next building but the building adjacent to that and to a corner of that building and to get there and tell us what was happening.  And so this robot was able to recruit other robots that acted as relays and they set up their own wireless ad hoc network.  And so I'm sitting here and I could actually in principle observe what was going on in a corner of the town building.  So you need lots of robots to do things like this.  And, again, often times we don't attack these kinds of problems unless we know that these problems are doable in the real world.  So that's an example of something we would not have attempted 10 years ago.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>What do you think are some of the coming challenges in robotics or some of the coming new problems?</interviewer>
<interviewee>I think one huge change I think is our ability to really develop three-dimensional autonomous flying robots.  The UAV industry is huge mostly because of these big drone aircrafts that fly at really high altitudes and do bad things that I don't care about.  But I think-- and they're very expensive.  But I think the time has sort of come that you can take those big objects and scale them down to really small objects and then make them completely autonomous.  So if you do that, I think the third dimension adds so much to robotics and if you look at the number of aerial robot sections and conferences, it's exploding.  I think-- so that's a big change in the next four to five years that we'll see coming.  </interviewee>
<interviewer>What do you see is the social or societal role of robotics if any?</interviewer>
<interviewee>You mean what role society has to play or the other way around?</interviewee>
<interviewer>Both, if you could answer both that would be great.</interviewer>
<interviewee>So I think the one thing-- so you may or may not know about this but there's a new robotics initiative that we're helping push through Washington and we hope they'll be funding for all kinds of new interesting projects both in academia and also in industry.  So this is called robotics 2.0.  So, as opposed to 1.0, 2.0 now acknowledges and emphasizes the role that humans play in a robotic society or the other way around, robots play in a human society.  And so the increasing-- the realization is that no matter what the application you want humans and robotics to work together and I think that is going to-- you're going to see more and more of that.  Already it happens in-- for example in the operating theatre where surgical robots are operated by surgeons and there's things happening together.  I think it happens a little bit in factories where you have humans working next to robots and the kinds of missions that I was talking about.  In Fukushima it's hard for humans to do it alone so they'll need robots.  On the other hand, robots will need to compliment humans and I think that that is going to-- you're going to see more and more of that.  And right now the only robot we have in our homes are vacuum cleaner robots partially because of economics, partially because of what society is willing to accept.  But I think you'll see a lot more of these kinds of robots in homes and I think it'll bridge the gap between humans and robots and I think you'll see a lot more of robots everywhere.  </interviewee>
</interview>
</subject>
